<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nero gallicanus, or, The true pourtraicture of Lewis XIV wherein the present war with France is justified, from the necessity of reducing that most Christian king to a more Christian temper.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52797</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12157842</idno>
  <idno type="VID">55190</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240916869</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing N439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14456</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12157842</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52797)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55190)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 611:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nero gallicanus, or, The true pourtraicture of Lewis XIV wherein the present war with France is justified, from the necessity of reducing that most Christian king to a more Christian temper.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by R. Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Europe --  History --  1648-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55190:1"/>
            <p>Nero Gallicanus: OR, THE TRUE POURTRAICTURE OF LEWIS XIV. Wherein the Present War with <hi>France</hi> is justified, from the necessity of reducing that Most CHRISTIAN KING to a more CHRISTIAN TEMPER.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Galli, ubi solitudinem fecerunt, pacem appellant.</hi>
               <bibl> Tacitus.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>R. Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:55190:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55190:2"/>
            <head>Nero Gallicanus, OR THE TRUE POURTRAICTURE OF Lewis the XIV.</head>
            <p>THere is no man Professing the Religion of <hi>Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> that can put a greater Scorn upon Heaven, or give a greater Testimony to the World of the slight opinion he has of the Trinity, which he pretendedly adores, than by assuming the Title of <hi>Most Christian,</hi> yet in all his Actions abjuring, and violating not only the Fundamental Precepts of Christian Religion, but even of Common Humanity and Morality. They are worse than Devils, who pretending to own the Sacred <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> leave nothing undone in opposition to God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. A great part of the <hi>Mythologie</hi> of the Heathens, is but a Description of the <hi>Most Christian King;</hi> under the Fables of <hi>Typhon,</hi> and the Gyants, warring against Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, setting forth his exorbitant Ambition, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of all Religion and Justice, and accounting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Sacred, nothing Honest, nothing Vertuous but his own Lawless Will and Pleasure: Under the Fable of <hi>Diomed,</hi> his inhuman Cruelty and Tyranny: Under the Fable of those <hi>Monsters,</hi> breathing out continual Fire, and consuming whole Regions and Countries with the flames that issued from their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55190:3"/>prodigious Jaws, his Depopulations and Devastations of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, his reducing whole Cities to Ashes, and exterminating Millions of poor People from their Rights and Possessions, without provocation given, on purpose to satisfie his insatiate Ambition. These were those Monsters of old, so much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembling the Most <hi>Christian Lewis</hi> the XIV. which by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients were look'd upon as the Nusances of the Earth; and for the subduing of which, so many Heroes were translated to the Stars, and so rewarded with Immortal Renown: A fair encouragement for the Heroes of this Age, of whom there are several that equal in Prowess and Conduct even <hi>Hercules</hi> himself, to sweep from the face of the Earth this enemy of Mankind, this common disturber of the Peace and Tranquillity of Christendom, this contradiction in Nature, the Most <hi>Christian</hi> Prosecutor of Christians, and the grand Actor of Impiety, Cruelty, Oppression, and Tyranny, upon the Stage of the World. When the Prophet cut <hi>Agag</hi> to pieces before the Lord in <hi>Gilgal,</hi> the sentence was very short which he pronounced upon the <hi>Amalekite</hi> Prince, but very comprehensive: <hi>As thy Sword has made Women Childless, so shall thy Mother be Childless among Women.</hi> Had the same Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice then been retaliated upon the Most <hi>Christian King,</hi> into how many bits would the Prophet's Indignation have minced him! But though the Prophet be in Heaven, who knows but the same Vengeance is now Prosecuting the Most <hi>Christian King</hi> by other Hands, since his Most Antichristian Sword, has not only made so many Mothers Childless, but so many Children Motherless. And that which heightens the Irreligion of all his unsanctified Actions is this; that Unmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lested, Unprovok'd, by Fraud and Surprize he despoil'd his Nighbour Princes of their long enjoy'd Possessions, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked their Cities, Plunder'd and Murther'd their Subjects un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of Airy Claims and Titles, merely to satisfie the insatiate Appetite of his Ambition, and engross the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Monarchy of <hi>Europe</hi> to himself. War, it is confess'd, has it's Justifications, but they must be bounded within the Limits of Justice and Moderation; which if a Prince provoked and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55190:3"/>affronted to the detriment of Himself and People pursues, and then be comes the Victor, his extent of Dominion may be envyed, but never condemned.</p>
            <p>On the other side if a Prince will be picking needless and fictitious Quarrels with his Nighbours, and be trampling, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the least disturbance or provocation given over, the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins of the Cities and Countries of his fellow Christians, mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to propagate Ambitious Empire, he becomes the <hi>Esau</hi> of the World, and while his hand is against all Men, if all men's hands are against him, it is no more than what the Laws of God and Nature justifie, upon the account of Self-defence and Preservation. And indeed there are few men that would not think, but that so fair and lovely a Portion of the Earth were enough to suffice any reasonable Prince, and that it were a labour sufficiently toilsome for a Sovereign Monarch, though never so wise and dexterous, to sustain the ponderous Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of so Populous a Nation, without desiring to heap more weight upon his shoulders; unless we could be induc'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it the extreme Charity of the Most <hi>Christian</hi> of Kings, out of his extraordinary pity of so many Nations of <hi>Europe</hi> under the mis-government of other Princes, to reduce them all under his more Provident, more Easie, and more Equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Dominion. But to that we can give no credit; when we find his own People so miserably Harras'd, Ransack'd, and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, that the whole Nation seems to Toil, Moil, Plough, Sow, Plant, and Trade for the benefit of one particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; where such is the deplorable Condition of the People, as would require a Pen of Iron dipt in tears of Bloud to describe it: Where a People naturally Active, Laborious, Sober. Industri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, inhabiting a Country fertile in Corn, in Wine, in Sheep, in Pasturage, in Oil, in Salt, and all sorts of Fruits; a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try water'd with many large Rivers, having the Ocean to the <hi>North,</hi> and <hi>West,</hi> and to the <hi>South,</hi> the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea; as if Nature, not content to have stor'd her with her own proper Products, would furnish her with all that Foreigners could afford her; where the People, I say, in the middst of such a Land, abounding with Milk and Honey, live in Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55190:4"/>of Straw, reduced to uttermost Beggary; where the poor Husband-man, after he has till'd and sow'd his Lands, when Harvest is over, has nothing but Rye, Barley, and Chest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts to eat, and for his drink nothing but water squeez'd through the Lee's of the Grapes, after the Wine is all prest out: For that the Collectors of the King's Duties carry away his Wheat, his Wine and Oil, leaving him hardly where withall to sow next year, and pay his Tithes. Besides that, the whole Country is charg'd with Duties of Exportation and Importation, together with excessive Customs and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posts; and to consume what the Toll-gathers leave, the Soldiers run from Province to Province, to complete the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series of the poor People.</p>
            <p>Since then the Most <hi>Christian King</hi> has so little <hi>Christian</hi> kindness for his own Subjects, it cannot be out of Charity that he seeks the Absolute Monarchy of <hi>Europe;</hi> but out of an insatiable desire to enrich himself with the spoils of all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> and to reduce the Subjects of other Princes, whose hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness he envies, under the same Bondage of his Arbitrary Will and Pleasure, that his own Subjects groan under. And in this eager chase of Universal Monarchy, such is the Rage of his Ambition to kill and take possession, that under the pretence of a Holy War to destroy <hi>Hereticks,</hi> he spares none, neither Priests nor Ministers, dissolves Religious Societies as well as Reformed Churches, demolishes Monasteries, as well as Temples, and draws his Sword against the <hi>Papists</hi> with the same violence, as against the followers of <hi>Calvin;</hi> seeking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Most <hi>Christian</hi> manner to establish his Will and Pleasure at any rate whatever; and not caring what Laws of Religion, Morality, and common Humanity he violates, to have the Lives, Estates, and Consciences of all the World at his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
            <p>This same Leprosie of Universal Dominion had long ago infected the <hi>French</hi> Monarchs, more especially <hi>Francis</hi> the I. who strongly stood in Competition for the Empire with <hi>Charles</hi> the V. and had engag'd several of the Electors on his side; but was frustrated in his expectations. Which so incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55190:4"/>him, that he proclaim'd War against the new made Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, in hopes to gain by force of Armes, what he could not gain by fair Means. And to facilitate his enterprize, was the first that taught the <hi>French</hi> the Most <hi>Christain</hi> Trick of Leaguing with the <hi>Turks,</hi> to the ruine of <hi>Christendom.</hi> Which prospered with him accordingly; for notwithstanding the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance that <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent gave him by two Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and sitting down before <hi>Vienna,</hi> his Wings were clipp'd by the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the V. by whom he was taken Prisoner at the Battel of <hi>Pavia,</hi> and carried Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner into <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Son <hi>Henry</hi> the II. pursu'd his Father's steps with much more Trechery, and for the time had better Luck, as having defeated <hi>Charles</hi> the V. in the Battel of <hi>Renty:</hi> But in the highth of his Successes was accidentally kill'd with the Splin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a Lance, as he was tilting with the Earl of <hi>Mongomery</hi> in a Turnament at the Nuptials of the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> with his Sister.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. is said to have had the same design; to which end a little before he was stabb'd by <hi>Ravillas,</hi> he had rais'd an Army of Threescore and Ten Thousand Men. Though others say, it was not so much to attain the Imperial Diadem, as it was to fetch back the Princess of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de</hi> from <hi>Brussells,</hi> whither the Prince her Husband had sent her, to free her from the King's Amorous Passion, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self from Dis-honour.</p>
            <p>The greatest part of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII's Reign was much dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted by intestine Broiles, and Civil Dissentions, during the continuance of which the House of <hi>Austria</hi> was near bringing all <hi>Germany</hi> under their Subjection, and after the Battel of <hi>Prague,</hi> through the remissness of King <hi>James,</hi> stood very fair for the Universal Empire. But then <hi>France</hi> having at last quieted all her domestick Disturbances, under pretence of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing the <hi>Austrian</hi> Family, while she was courted by several Princes to Assist and Protect them against the Emperour, vast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encreased her own Power, and enlarged her Dominions by the Conquest of new Provinces, and the Acquisition of several
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55190:5"/>considerable Town in <hi>Italy, Spain, Germany,</hi> and the <hi>Spanish Netherlands;</hi> which raising new Jealousies among her own Allies, occasioned the Peace of <hi>Munster,</hi> to prevent the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Progress of her Arms.</p>
            <p>Hence it is apparent that the <hi>French</hi> Kings, for several A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, have still, out of a restless and ambitious humour, been endeavouring to get ground upon their Neighbours, and to enlarge their own Dominions, always have been laying hold of all opportunities to disturb Mankind; never being able to set bounds to their Ambition: And therefore that it ever was, and ever will be the true Interest of <hi>Europe</hi> to oppose the <hi>French</hi> designs; or if there be any occasion at any time to make use of their assistance, not to accept of it any longer, than the publick benefit requires it, nor to suffer them to proceed when once the Danger is over, as was practised by the Peace of <hi>Passau,</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> II. and that of <hi>Munster,</hi> by both which the <hi>French</hi> were stopp'd in their full Career by their own Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, though they still came off with advantage.</p>
            <p>For there is nothing more certain, than that <hi>France</hi> can never grow great, but by usurping upon her Neighbours, as of late through the impolitick kindnesses of the two last Reigns she has done to the purpose; wherein she fails not to use Address and Policy by another name, called <hi>Fas</hi> and <hi>Nefas,</hi> to attain her ends: And thus it was that <hi>Henry</hi> the III. of <hi>France,</hi> under the pretence of sending succours to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants of <hi>Germany,</hi> took <hi>Mentz.</hi> In short, he sent away the Constable <hi>Montmorancy,</hi> with fourty thousand Men, in shew to that intent; and to that purpose desired free passage for his Men through <hi>Mentz,</hi> which at that time was for the most part of the same Religion with those in <hi>Germany;</hi> and therefore in no good Correspondence with the Emperour. They joyfully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to the Kings demand, and as a Testimony of their good will; they set up Tables in the streets, furnish'd with Victuals and Drink, for the refreshment of the Soldiers in their March, with many other great marks of Friendship and Rejoycing: But their Joy was soon chang'd into Tears, for so soon as the Cunstable (who was receiv'd by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55190:5"/>with all the Testimonies of respect and kindness ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, was enter'd into the City; he feigned himself to be feiz'd with a fit of the Gout, and to be tormented with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessive Pains, insomuch that he declared his desire to make his last Will, not knowing what might befall him in the War, which he was about to undertake; and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sir'd all the Magistrates of the City to be present as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses. But before this he had given Order to two of his principal Commanders, one to seize the Gate at which the Soldiers march'd in, and the other to take possession of the Gate, through which the Soldiers march'd out: The first was also to cause that part of the Army that was not enter'd to advance, and the second was to call back those that were already march'd out. And then it was that the Constable see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Magistracy and principall Gentry of the City stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about his Bed-side in expectation of his Orders, started on a sudden from his pretended Bed of Pain, like an enraged Lyon, and stabb'd the Mayor of the Town with his Dagger to the Heart; upon which signal given, his Guards entered the Chamber and assassinated all the Nobility, and at the same time the Soldiers ran through the streets, crying out, <hi>The City is taken.</hi> And thus was <hi>Mentz</hi> immediately secur'd, plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, and subjected under the Bloody Dominion of the <hi>French</hi> King, and of an <hi>Ally,</hi> which it was before, become an enslaved Village. And this was one of the Conquests of <hi>Henry</hi> the III.</p>
            <p>In like manner <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII. Sir-named the <hi>Just,</hi> with the Title of most <hi>Christian</hi> to boot, not knowing how to make himself Master of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> by the advice of Cardinal <hi>Richlieu,</hi> that blessed Saint, came to <hi>Lyons</hi> with an Army. Of this the <hi>Cardinal</hi> sent <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> notice, and word withall, that it would be requisite for him to wait upon the King to tender him his respects, and to assure him by word of Mouth of his good Intentions towards his Royal Person. Accordingly the Duke, not dreaming of any thing, went to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute his Majesty, whom he found at the Head of his Army. But when he had perform'd his Complements, and thought to have returned home again, he found himself in the Lyon's
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55190:6"/>Den, being arrested under pretence of some old differences. But then his <hi>Eminency</hi> stept in under the disguise of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercessor, and pretending to make his peace, undertook to procure his Liberty, upon the surrender of <hi>Nants,</hi> the chief City and Key of his <hi>Dutchy;</hi> which for the sake of his Liberty the Duke was forc'd to doe and so the King enter'd with his Army like a Conqueror. And thus the World may see the real Honesty and Integrity of <hi>France,</hi> under <hi>Henry</hi> the III. and <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Just;</hi> and that she is <hi>semper eadem,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any alteration, you shall find by the sequel of this short Discourse.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII. succeeded the Most <hi>Christian</hi> (as he styles himself) <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. in his Minority, under the Tuition and Counsels of Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> the true Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Cardinal <hi>Richlieu,</hi> both Men in Holy Orders, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendedly devoted to the Service of God; but in the whole practice of their Lives abandon'd to the Finesses, and most Infernal part of State Politicks; who forsaking the paths of Vertue, and Sincerity, and wholly neglecting the Divine Precepts of Justice, and Plain-dealing, set them by their Great Lord and Master Christ, whose Ministers in an high Station they pretended to be, apply'd their whole Studies to advance the Reign of Rapine and Injustice, and to let loose all the Powers of Wickedness and Mischief upon the Earth. And as for <hi>Mazarine,</hi> having so fertile a <hi>Genius</hi> to manure, as that of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. it was no wonder he became so prompt a Pupil, and so great a Proficient in all the <hi>Super-Matchiavil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Doctrines, which his <hi>Eminency</hi> had infus'd into his Most <hi>Christian</hi> Mind. So that he had no sooner put on the Robes of Manhood, but he began to act the young <hi>Nimrod,</hi> to hunt after the name of <hi>Great,</hi> and as if already he had had the promise of the Grand Tempter of all, <hi>These will I give thee,</hi> for falling down and worshipping, to believe all <hi>Europe</hi> his own by right of infernal Contract; he seem'd to scorn the petty name of King, while nothing would serve his Mind, but the more lofty Title of <hi>Sultan</hi> of the fourth part of the World.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:55190:6"/>
            <p>True it is, that notwithstanding the Convulsions that threatned his Kingdom during his Minority, yet <hi>Mazarine</hi> having by a Conjunction with <hi>Cromwell,</hi> surmounted all those difficulties, much increased his Power, and inlarged his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests by new Acquisitions: (For <hi>Cromwell,</hi> whom for his pains <hi>Mazarine</hi> was wont to call a <hi>Fortunate</hi> Fool,) gaping after the Golden Mines of <hi>Peru,</hi> to supply his empty Coffers, contrary to all the Rules of <hi>English</hi> Policy, was altogether for pulling down the distant Monarchy of <hi>Spain,</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing the neighbouring power of <hi>France. Mazarine</hi> had the length of his Foot; and therefore resolv'd to make the best of him, by pampering up his Gold craving humour, and fostering his Animosities against the <hi>Spaniard.</hi> And so cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was <hi>Mazarine,</hi> that he granted the heedless Usurper what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he demanded, considering that when <hi>Cromwell</hi> had as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted him to doe his work, in bringing under the House of <hi>Austria,</hi> and by that means casting the Balance of <hi>Europe</hi> on the <hi>French</hi> side, he should afterwards have leisure enough to recover what he had seem'd to part with; which was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards too unhappily verified by the easie regaining of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk.</hi> Thus <hi>Cromwell</hi> being the first that rais'd the <hi>Grandeur</hi> of the <hi>French,</hi> to which he contributed not a little by the War which he made at the time with <hi>Spain;</hi> the two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that succeeded him, were so wheedled and bewitched by the <hi>French</hi> Kings specious pretencees and fair Promises, that they did, tho undesignedly too much assist, him to get up to the Pinicle of Universal Dominion; as if this Most <hi>Christian</hi> King had made use of Charms and Philters to fas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinate their Eyes and Ears, neither to see themselves so often abus'd, nor to hear the advices of their most faithfull Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellours.</p>
            <p>How happy was the King of <hi>England,</hi> at his first Restaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, belov'd by his People, ador'd by his Parliament, and in perfect Union with his Nighbours the <hi>Dutch!</hi> What might not those two Potentates in close Confederacy have done? <hi>France</hi> trembled at the thoughts of it, and despair'd of gras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55190:7"/>Universal Empire, unless she could divide this solid op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, so pernicious to her soaring Projects.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King well understood that the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> would he but put himself to the trouble of knowing his own strength, and making a true use of it, was in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not only to mediate, but to force a Peace among all the Potentates of <hi>Europe.</hi> For by a strict Union with the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> he was absolute Master of the whole <hi>Ocean,</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of the Riches of the World; insomuch that the Mines of <hi>America,</hi> were not safe to the King of <hi>Spain</hi> but by his Permission; and by sending to the weaker side the assis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of his Land Forces, formidable as well for their Courage as their Discipline, he was able to have turn'd the scales of Victory which way soe'er he pleas'd. Now then in regard that by the common Rules of Policy and Fore-sight, the <hi>French</hi> King could not but be well assur'd that whatsoever Princes he assail'd, the other would be as certain in the weakness of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to have recourse to the two Grand Fortresses of <hi>Europe,</hi> Potent at Sea, and no less powerfull by Land, to prevent the Ravage of his Territories; whether the Dictates of <hi>Achitophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lism,</hi> and <hi>Matchavillinism,</hi> might not in some measure justifie the most <hi>Christian</hi> King, in pursuing the best Methods he could, to separate such a Conjunction, so prejudicial to his aspiring Ambition and Self-interest, may not be so much, perhaps the Question; but whether he is not to be look'd upon, as the worst of the whole Race of <hi>Cain,</hi> and as a Mischief, and Pest which all Mankind ought to eschew; who, besides the most unchristianlike ways by which he sought to subdue his Enemies, treated his most faithfull Friends and Allies with that Infidelity, that Treachery, that base and scornfull Ingratitude as he did the King of <hi>England.</hi> By which it was plain, that all the Kindnesses and Remuneration which the Most <hi>Christian Lewis</hi> intended the King of <hi>England</hi> for all his Services, was only that he should have been the last, that for all his Services and Assistences given to the <hi>French</hi> Crown, to the over-sight of his own Interest, and his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55190:7"/>Peoples welfare, should have been rewarded with Invasion and Conquest.</p>
            <p>To make this Separation therefore between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> the most subtile <hi>Mercuries</hi> of <hi>France</hi> were sent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad with their Silver Wands, to lull the British <hi>Argos</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sleep, and prevent his watching over the <hi>Hesperian</hi> Garden of <hi>European</hi> Liberty; or rather with a deeper Intoxication of <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> Draughts, to allure his Ministers into a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Falsification of their Trusts. Nor was it possible for all of them to escape, being befascinated or to resist those Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Temptations; but, like People that must go through with what they have taken money to perform, presently se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral artificial insinuations of Injuries receiv'd from the <hi>Dutch,</hi> as to <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and the Fishery, were whisper'd about in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> while at the same time the freedom of the Sea, and the preservation of <hi>Trade,</hi> were with the same subtilty to be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted in <hi>Holland,</hi> on purpose to exasperate the jealousie of those People. Things that might so easily have been adjusted where there had been the least Condescentions to Reason, that it was undoubtedly above the reach of most Mens un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, that the Policy of Great <hi>Britain</hi> should prefer a trivial Quarrel about <hi>Sprats</hi> and <hi>Herrings,</hi> (for the business of <hi>Amboyna</hi> had been compounded long before,) above the common safety of three Nations, and that a Protestant Kingdom, without being constrained thereto by some unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable necessity, should ever fight with so much Rage and Fierceness for the Destruction of the Protestant Interest: Or that <hi>English</hi> Counsellors should advise their Prince to run the Fortune of a <hi>French</hi> King, without any rational Prospect of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to himself. But it was plain that the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King was then laying his most <hi>Ʋnchristian</hi> Trains for the Destruction of <hi>England;</hi> and as palpable it was, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> War was design'd by the <hi>French</hi> to ruine the naval strength of both Nations, and thereby to break the Balance of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi> It was a Mystery beyond unfolding, that the Chief Ministers of <hi>England</hi> should take such strange Measures, so to mislead their Sovereign, that in order to the making good
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55190:8"/>his Title to the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> he should enable the <hi>French</hi> King to invade all Christendom, and to extend his Empire beyond all bounds; or that to secure to himself and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Sovereignty of the Seas, he should with so much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry endeavour to force all the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships, with all their Naval Power, into the Arms of the <hi>French,</hi> and rejoyce at their Victories as if by Conquering the Land, the <hi>French</hi> did not at the same time become Masters of the Havens, Rivers, and Fleets of the <hi>Dutch.</hi> And yet such was the vast Predominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which <hi>French</hi> Treason, and the hidden Conspiracies of <hi>French</hi> Counsels had over these great Politicians, and the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendent which they had over the King of <hi>England,</hi> that he was so kind to the <hi>French</hi> King, for setting him together by the ears with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> that he sent him his Vice Admirals, and other Sea Officers, to encourage and promote the setting out of his Fleets, and in pity of their want of experience in Sea Affairs, took his raw Seamen by the hand, train'd them up in his own Fleets, among the best of his Seamen, and taught them that skill which the <hi>English</hi> had been many Ages a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and all this in hopes to enable the <hi>French</hi> King to assist him in beating his best and most secure friends; wherein the <hi>French,</hi> according to their wonted Treachery, fail'd him too, when they were put to the Tryall.</p>
            <p>All the World would have thought the King should not have so soon forgot the <hi>Punic</hi> Faith of <hi>France</hi> in their kindness to his Person, while he was abroad in Exile among them; or if then they might pretend the Interest of their Kingdom, and palliate their faithless and inhumane Dealing with him by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of Self-preservation; yet no such necessity constrain'd him to forget the <hi>French</hi> King's opposing his Restauration with so much violence as he did; and his Caballing with his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test enemies to keep him out of his Kingdom, more especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly since he was then so sensible of it, when it was recent in his Memory; that upon his coming into <hi>England,</hi> he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded away Monsieur <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Ambassadour, and would not suffer him to come into his presence.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55190:8"/>
            <p>But the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King knew full well how to work himself again into the King of <hi>England</hi>'s favour, and at length by throwing a <hi>French Dalilah</hi> into his embraces, quite cut off the Locks of the <hi>British</hi> Sampson. All on a sudden <hi>France</hi> seem'd to be remov'd into <hi>England;</hi> nothing but <hi>French</hi> Bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Gugaws pleased our <hi>English</hi> Gentry: A <hi>French</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction prevailing at Court, <hi>French</hi> Mountebanks for Physici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>French</hi> Fashions, <hi>French</hi> Hats, <hi>French</hi> Lackeys, <hi>French</hi> Fidlers, <hi>French</hi> Dancing-Masters, <hi>French</hi> Tooth-Drawers, <hi>French</hi> Barbers, <hi>French</hi> Air in our very looks, <hi>French</hi> Legs, <hi>French</hi> Compliments, <hi>French</hi> Grimaces, and <hi>French</hi> Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, to fit us for <hi>French</hi> Slavery: And had the <hi>French</hi> Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease been then unknown in <hi>England,</hi> 'tis to be questioned whither it would not have been entertained with as general a Consent as the <hi>Sichemites</hi> submitted to the Pain of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision, though to the hazard of being all destroy'd by the <hi>French Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> while sore and driveling under the Distemper. Nor is it to be doubted but the <hi>French</hi> Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity would have as easily made tryall of such a Design as they did of the rest of their Tricks, had they thought it would have taken effect.</p>
            <p>It is well known, that before the first <hi>Dutch</hi> War was entred into, the King of <hi>England</hi> sought to make Alliances with <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> but the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were so Cock-sure of the <hi>French</hi> Promises, that they would not make any Approaches to Friendship with <hi>England,</hi> without the giving up of <hi>Dunkirk, Tangier,</hi> and <hi>Jamaica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>French,</hi> a Project of a Treaty was offer'd them, and promoted with all earnestness by the Lord <hi>H—s</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> but it was plainly discern'd that the principal designs of the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King was only to draw the King of <hi>England</hi> into such an Alliance, as might advance his design upon <hi>Spain;</hi> and therefore so soon as he had set the <hi>Dutch</hi> and us together by the Ears, and saw that thereby the Balance of <hi>Europe</hi> was broken, he no longer minded Alliance with <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland:</hi> But after many Proposals of Leagues, and many Arts used to highten the jealousies between Us and the <hi>Hollanders,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:55190:9"/>he at last sided with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> though to so little purpose, that his Intentions plainly appeared to be no other, than to see the two most Potent Obstacles of his Ambition destroy one another, to the end he might with less Opposition invade his Nighbours, and increase his own Naval Strength. Nay, the Juggle went much farther, for that in the heat of all the War, he still kept Negotiations on Foot, and made overtures and proposals of Peace, by means of the Queen-Mother, whom in the end he so far, and so treacherously deluded, as to ascer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her, and by her means to assure the King of <hi>England</hi> her Son, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> would not set out any Fleet the ensuing Summer, and yet underhand press'd the <hi>Dutch</hi> with all the Vigor and Importunity imaginable to fit out their Men of War again, with a promise, rather than fail, that he would joyn his Fleet with theirs against the <hi>English.</hi> Now it was upon a Supposal that the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King was at that time a good Christian and true to his Word, in pursuing his pretended Proposals of Peace; and upon that faithless <hi>French</hi> Paroll it was, that the King of <hi>England</hi> put forth no Fleet to Sea that Year, upon which followed that Fatal surprize of our Ships at <hi>Chatham;</hi> then which a greater Dis-honour never hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to the Nation since the memory of History. But at last, as we had been oblig'd to the Craft and Treachery for the War and the Shame we received by it, so we were glad to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Peace that ensued from his favour; which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded at <hi>Breda</hi> between <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this Treaty of <hi>Breda,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> were oblig'd to restore St. <hi>Christophers</hi> to the <hi>English</hi> in the same manner and form as is exprest in the Articles; but instead of performing their Engagement according to the true intent and literal meaning of the Articles, they from time to time upon several unjust and frivolous Pretences, deluded and delay'd the <hi>English</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners that were sent to take Possession of it; till finding there was a necessity to comply with us in so small a matter, while we were preparing to venture a second quarrel in their behalf, it was at last surrendred, after four year's baffling, to Sir <hi>Charles Wheeler.</hi> However to shew the perfidiousness
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55190:9"/>of <hi>French</hi> dealing, before they deliver'd it they destroyed all the Plantations, laid the whole Island waste, and left it in a much worse condition than if it had never been planted. And as if the seizure and detaining of the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories had not been sufficient, they interrupted also the Trade of his Subjects in those Parts, and assuming to themselves the Sovereignty of those Seas, would not suffer any Ships but their own, to sail either by or about those Islands; but as if it had been Criminal so to doe, took and confiscated several Vessels up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account. From all which a Question will arise easie to be resolv'd, whither any thing be recorded of the old <hi>Carthaginians</hi> more perfidious than this; and whether the King of <hi>England</hi> might not have expected more Honest and Christian dealing from the <hi>unbelieving Turk,</hi> than from the Most <hi>Christian King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, that after the Peace of <hi>Breda,</hi> the King of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> was at liesure to consider how the <hi>French</hi> King had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd him, by engaging him in a War with his Protestant Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and how he had seemingly taken their parts to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the War; that while they were battering, and bruising, and weakning one another, he might have the fairer Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, in violation of all the most solemn and sacred Oaths and Treaties, to invade the <hi>Spanish</hi> Netherlands; and obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with what a rapid Torrent of Victory he bore down all before him, thought fit to interpose before the flame that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed his next Nighbour, should throw it's sparks over the Water; and therefore sent into <hi>Holland</hi> to invite them to a nearer Alliance, and to enter into such farther Counsels as were most proper to stop the Fury of the <hi>French</hi> King; which offer being by the <hi>Dutch</hi> embraced with open Arms, a defensive League was concluded in five days time between <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with another for the repressing the farther Progress of the <hi>French</hi> Armes in the <hi>Spanish</hi> Netherlands: In which the <hi>Sweeds</hi> afterwards making a third Party concern'd, gave it the name of the Triple League.</p>
            <p>This was no way pleasing to the <hi>French</hi> King, however for a while he dissembled his resentment of the Affront, though from the first moment he resolved to make use of all his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55190:10"/>Charms, and Golden Magick to dissolve this Triple Knot, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it cost him.</p>
            <p>To this purpose the Duchess of <hi>Orleance,</hi> is said by the <hi>French</hi> to be sent over hither, believing no Instrument so proper as the King of <hi>England</hi>'s own Sister to prevail with her Brother. King <hi>Charles</hi> met her at <hi>Dover,</hi> where their endearments one to another were so much the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally prevailing, by how much it happens that Princes more rarely than private Persons enjoy their Relations: And when they doe, yet their kind Interviews are many times at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with some fatal disaster; of which though there was no appearance here in <hi>England,</hi> yet the first News we heard of her upon her Return to <hi>France,</hi> was, that she was dead: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Affair was so dextrously managed, that a <hi>French</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadour was forthwith dispatch'd out of <hi>France,</hi> and an <hi>English</hi> Ambassadour sent to <hi>Paris,</hi> and as the <hi>French</hi> gave out, a private League was clapt up, to the ruine of the Triple Alliance, to all the highth of Intimacy and Dearness; as if upon dissecting the Princess, there had some State <hi>Philter</hi> been found in her Bowels, or that a Reconciliation with <hi>France</hi> could not have been celebrated with a less Sacrifice than that of the Bloud-Royal of <hi>England.</hi> This supposed Treaty was a work of Darkness, not to be div'd into in a great while, but afterwards the <hi>French</hi> King caus'd it to be made publick, as we shall see by and by.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the Knowledg of this was of great Importance to <hi>England;</hi> but the discovery was the most apparent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration in the World of <hi>French</hi> Perfidiousness, so enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous as it could not be imagined to have entred into the Breast of a Most <hi>Christian</hi> King, so treacherously to expose the Secrets of his dearest Confederate, after he had drawn him in by all the Assurances of his assistance imaginable: And the reasons that induc'd him to make the detection were no less Impious, though agreeable to the Practice of the <hi>French</hi> King; who after he has made it his business to decoy in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that lend an easie ear to his Enchantments, or with too much facility suffer themselves to be overcome by his Allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Engagements, into any unseemly and dishonourable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55190:10"/>believes he has them then safely tack'd to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests, and that they will not dare to flinch from his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings, for fear of being exposed to their People, which he takes care in due time to have artificially instill'd into their Ears; a Maxim of Christianity which lies conceal'd from all other Men, but the most <hi>Christian</hi> of Princes: And thus it was, that the <hi>French</hi> King having amus'd the Emperor with the Noise of a Treaty, and at the same time brought the <hi>Turk</hi> into <hi>Hungary,</hi> to joyn the Malecontents, to excite his Private Confederate the King of <hi>England</hi> to follow his steps in Government Bare-faced, causes a little Book to be Printed and Published, with the Privilege <hi>Du Roy,</hi> Entitl'd, The <hi>History of the Transactions of this Age,</hi> and therein ordered the <hi>Dover Treaty</hi> (as they call'd it) to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted, and to that purpose furnish'd his <hi>Historiographer</hi> with Notes and Directions by the Hands of his Secretary <hi>Colbert,</hi> to the end that the King of <hi>England,</hi> being truly as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd, set out in his Colours, and despairing of being ever after trusted by his People, might be enforced to take such Resolutions as <hi>Despair</hi> and <hi>Fury</hi> should inspire him withall, to the Destruction of those he had so highly disoblig'd; there being nothing more than the Subversion of <hi>England</hi> which the <hi>French</hi> King aim'd at. 'Tis true, he was so kind as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call the <hi>Book,</hi> upon the loud complaint of the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s Ambassador; however it was an apparent Demonstrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all the World, how little trust or reliance there was in <hi>French</hi> Amity, and plainly shews that there is no way to bind this mighty <hi>Sampson</hi> by Oath, Promises, Treaties, or by any other the most Religious Ties and Considerations, which are no more to him than Spiders Webs, but by an absolute clipping off the Locks of his Power, and disabling him so as never to rise more.</p>
            <p>But to return to the <hi>Triple League:</hi> In the end the <hi>French</hi> King by his wicked Policy so contrived the matter, as to cause a new Rupture 'twixt the <hi>Dutch</hi> and the <hi>English;</hi> and as if he had intended to be the Master of Iniquity, and to make the King of <hi>England</hi> as bad as himself; nothing would
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55190:11"/>suffice till he had prevail'd with the King to attack the <hi>Dutch Smyrna</hi> Fleet returning home, and dreaming of no such matter; which, as it was contrary to the <hi>Genius</hi> of the <hi>English</hi> Nation, and to the Nature and Gentle Disposition of the King of <hi>England</hi> himself, is wholly to be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Wiles and wicked Temptations of the Most <hi>Christian</hi> Prince, who never ceas'd pealing it into the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Ears, that if he could but master the Wealth of the <hi>Smyrna</hi> Fleet, he should never want Mony again. And being thus betrayed by wheedling <hi>French</hi> Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucination, what can the <hi>French</hi> expect but the Severity of <hi>England</hi>'s just Revenge; wherein we may venture with the greater hopes of Success, as being engaged with all in the common Cause of Christendoms Tranquillity.</p>
            <p>Add to this, that when the <hi>French</hi> King thought the King of <hi>England</hi> was engaged so far by the <hi>Smyrna Attack,</hi> as that he must needs go forward, the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King then open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared, 'twas none of his Quarrel, and that he only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in it to assist the King of <hi>England,</hi> merely in respect to His Person: By which means the King of <hi>England</hi> was again betrayed and necessitated to declare War first, and to expect the Assistance of his Confederate afterwards.</p>
            <p>Nor is it less observable, that the <hi>French</hi> King, in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with a Protestant Prince, to render him odious among all the States and Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> whether Protestant or Roman Catholick, gave it out, that the War against the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces was a War of Religion, undertaken merely for the Propagation of the Roman Catholick Faith, and as the <hi>French</hi> Minister expressed it in a Solemn Speech to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror's Council, that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> being Heroticks, who had forsaken God, all good Christians were bound to Unite to their Extirpation. To confirm which the more, the <hi>French</hi> Ministers, no doubt not contrary to their Instructions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd and assur'd many Princes, that to let all the World see how far their Master was from any such Ambitious designs as were laid to his charge, and to satisfie the World that he entred into the War merely out of a Religious Zeal, and for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55190:11"/>the Glory of God; he was ready to part with all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests, and to restore to the <hi>Hollanders</hi> all the Towns he had won from them, if they would but re-establish the True Worship they had banish'd out of their Dominions. Such is the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King, who scruples not to falsifie with Heaven, so it may but support and colour his falshood upon Earth.</p>
            <p>Well, the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King, having by his Ungodly Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy thus engaged us in a Bloudy War with <hi>Holland,</hi> pursues his own design by Land with all the Vigour Imaginable, in so much, that the swiftness and force of his Motion seem'd to be somewhat Supernatural; but all this while he leaves us to doe our own work by Sea. 'Tis true, his Fleet appeared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, and made up a third Squadron under white Colours, but under that Colour of Innocence, they thought it such a crime to shed Bloud, that they always kept out of harms way: Rather they did us more mischief than good, in regard that when our Admirals encountr'd the Enemy in hopes of their Assistance, they always left the <hi>English</hi> in the Lurch to bear the Brunt of the Engagement against the superiour Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which it was their Duty to have attack'd. A peice of Treachery so insupportable, that only they who suffer'd it would have endur'd it, by which the whole <hi>English</hi> Navy was absolutely betrayed by a faithless Allie, and by which the Lives of great numbers of the <hi>English</hi> were lost, which by their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction might have been sav'd. So that it was apparent that those sacred Ships of the <hi>French</hi> were a sort of <hi>Noli me Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere's,</hi> not sent to assist their Confederares, but only to sound the <hi>English</hi> Seas, to spy our Ports, to learn our Building, to contemplate our way of Fighting, to consume ours, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve their own Navy, to encrease their Commerce, and to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all so, that the two great Naval Powers of <hi>Europe</hi> having crush'd one another, he might remain sole Lord of the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and by consequence Master of all the Trade of the World,</p>
            <p>Thus it happen'd, that after three Engagements of Ours against the <hi>Dutch Fleet</hi> in one Summer, while nothing was
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55190:12"/>tenable at Land against the <hi>French,</hi> it seem'd that as to us every thing at Sea was Impregnable; which was not to be attributed either to want of Courage or Conduct, but was only to be imputed to our unfortunate Conjunction with the perfidious <hi>French,</hi> like the misfortunes that happen to Men by being in ill Company.</p>
            <p>This Misbehaviour of the <hi>French</hi> rais'd the Indignation of the <hi>English</hi> to such a Pitch, that the Parliament resolving to give no more Mony for the continuance of the War, the King was persuaded to make a Peace with <hi>Holland;</hi> which was concluded accordingly, toward the latter end of the Year 1673.</p>
            <p>And to shew that the King of <hi>England</hi> had all the reason in the World so to doe, we are to take a little farther prospect of the uprightness of the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King to his Friend and Allie, who had at such a vast expence of Treasure espous'd his Quarrel.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>French</hi> Army having passed the <hi>Wale,</hi> caus'd such a General Consternation all over <hi>Holland,</hi> and the Confusion they were in was such, they could hardly resolve whether to yield or continue to defend themselves. The States there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore sent away several of their Deputies, some to the King of <hi>England,</hi> others to the Most <hi>Christian</hi> of Princes, to know of both upon what conditions they would be willing to make Peace and Agreement.</p>
            <p>Those that were sent to the King of <hi>England</hi> (to shew how justly he intended to have dealt with the <hi>French,</hi> or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were out of Fear of giving him any Jealousie or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,) were met as far as <hi>Gravesend,</hi> and being forbid their approach to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> were conveigh'd to <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> and there, as it were, honourably confin'd, till his Majesty of <hi>England</hi> could hear from the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King, whether those Deputies might be admitted.</p>
            <p>But the other Deputies no sooner arriv'd at the <hi>French Court,</hi> but two Secretaries of State were sent to them, who, without farther delay, demanded in the first place what Power they had to Treat; and next, what Proposals they had to make in order to a speedy Peace.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:55190:12"/>
            <p>The Deputies answered, they came not to make Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals, but to recieve Conditions from his Most <hi>Christian</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, as it better became them. Upon which, to hasten them to a Conclusion, the <hi>French Ministers</hi> told them in short, That whatever his Most <hi>Christian</hi> Majesty had conquer'd, in their Dominions, he lookt upon as his own already, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would not part with it, without an Equivalent, as well for what he might farther subdue, before the conclusion of the Treaty, as for what he had already in Possession.</p>
            <p>With this Answer Monsieur <hi>De Groet,</hi> one of the <hi>Holland</hi> Deputies, posted back to the <hi>Hague,</hi> and with no less speed was sent back again with full Instructions and Authority, jointly with the rest of his Colleagues, to treat and conclude a Peace with them.</p>
            <p>No sooner was he return'd, but Monsieur <hi>Louvoy,</hi> one of the <hi>French</hi> King's Secretaries, gave the Deputies a Draught of a Treaty, or rather the Pretensions of the King his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster; upon the granting of which, he was both willing and ready to return to his former Amity with the States, and to conclude a firm Peace with them.</p>
            <p>Upon which two things are Observable. First, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions themselves were such, which, if granted, would have made the <hi>French</hi> King as perfectly Master of the Country, as if he had Conquer'd it by the Sword. And, in the Second place, That in all the Articles there was not the least word relating to <hi>England,</hi> nor any more notice taken of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> than if he had not been at all concern'd in the War.</p>
            <p>And farther, to demonstrate that it was never the design of the Most <hi>Christian</hi> Prince, that the King of <hi>England</hi> should be a gainer by the War, Monsieur <hi>De Groet</hi> declared at his second return to the <hi>Hague,</hi> when he carryed the King's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject along with him, that when the <hi>French</hi> Ministers were ask'd what was to be done with <hi>England,</hi> they made Answer, that the States might doe as they pleas'd with <hi>England,</hi> and come off as cheap as they could, for that the <hi>French</hi> were not bound by their Treaty to procure them any Advantages. A great Happiness in the mean time for the King of <hi>England</hi> to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55190:13"/>be engaged in such a War, with such a False and Treacherous Allie; for it is plain, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> had no sooner signifi'd their desires, but the Most <hi>Christian</hi> Prince had it presently in his Head to have cheated the King of <hi>England.</hi> For could the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King in that same dreadful Consternation of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> have got the Possession of the United Provinces by the more concise, and less expensive way of Treaty, he would soon have found an expedient to have defrauded his dear Confederate of any share in them. Which was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son the Most <hi>Christian</hi> Sophister spurr'd on the consternated <hi>Dutch</hi> with so much haste, and with such a clandestine speed pursu'd his Advantage, that the King of <hi>England</hi> might not have a Moment's time to provide for himself.</p>
            <p>But the King of <hi>England</hi> having serv'd the Most <hi>Christian</hi> Prince more justly in his kind, by a separate Peace with <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the sudden Advancement of His Highness the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> attended by the Fall of the <hi>De-witts,</hi> quash'd all the lofty <hi>Frenchman's</hi> hopes of gaining, either by Treaty or by Conquests, what his thoughts aspir'd to. So that now, as if he had been arriv'd at the <hi>Tropick</hi> of his Fortune, he was forc'd to roll back again with the same swiftness as he ascended to the highth of his success. However that he might not lose his old wont, as a mark of his displeasure, and as it were to punish the <hi>English</hi> Nation for his disappointments, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Peace that was still firm between the two Crowns, he let loose his Privateers among the <hi>English</hi> Merchants, to that degree of <hi>Treaty-Violation,</hi> that from that time for near two years together (Peace all the while, if <hi>French Peace</hi> may be call'd <hi>Peace,</hi>) there was no security of Commerce or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, but at Sea they Murther'd, Plunder'd, made Prize, and Confiscated all they met with. The <hi>French</hi> Pickaroons lay before the Mouths of our Harbors, hover'd all along our Coasts, took our Ships in the very Ports, so that we were in a manner Blockt up by Water. And if any made Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the Sovereign Port of the Most <hi>Christian Solyman</hi> for Justice, they were most insolently baffled, except some few who by Sir <hi>E. L</hi>'s interest were redeem'd upon somewhat
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55190:13"/>easter Composition. For evidence of which the following Papers, return'd by certain Members of the Privy Council, in Pursuance of the King's Order, as also the Register which was annex'd to it, of the several Vessels that were then complain'd of to be taken, are a Memorial not easie to be cancell'd.</p>
            <p>So loud and so thick were the daily complaints of the <hi>English</hi> Merchants, of their losses sustain'd by the <hi>French</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vateers, in the Year 1674. and 1676. notwithstanding the Publick Amity between the two Nations, that the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd the Examination thereof to several Lords of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Trade, who, upon due Examination of the Affair, observ'd that the Petition of the Merchants, presented to the King the 31st. of <hi>May,</hi> 1676. was grounded upon these Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> That their Ships and Goods, though mann'd accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Act of Navigation, and furnish'd with all necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Passes, were daily seiz'd, carry'd into <hi>Dunkirk, Calais, Sherbrook,</hi> and other Ports, the Masters and Owners kept close Prisoners, to force them by hardship to abuse their Owners, or else for the relief of their own private Necessities (being commonly Stripp'd and Plunder'd) to enter into the Privateers Service, which great numbers had done with very pernicious Effects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the delay and charge of prosecuting the Law in <hi>France,</hi> did commonly make the Owners become losers of half the Value, when ever they were successfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That there was no reparation ever gotten from Privateers for what they Plunder'd and Imbezl'd, which made them freely seize upon all they met, and perpetually molest the Navigation of the King's Subjects; for which Reasons they humbly implor'd His Majesty's Relief and Protection.</p>
            <p>Thereupon the King was pleas'd to command that some of his Frigats should sail forth to clear the Coast of those Privateers, seize them, and bring such as had offended to make Restitution. Moreover the King order'd, that the Lords of the Committee of Trade should take good notice of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Cases and Complaints depending, that such as were
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55190:14"/>of weight and merit, might be fitted for his Gracious Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation for Relief: As also to survey the whole number of Seizures which had been made upon his Subjects, in order to lay before his Majesty what hardships had been sustain'd at Sea, and what sort of Justice had been administer'd in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Obedience to which command, they brought in a List of such Ships as had been seiz'd to the number of fifty three; and the Cases wherein the Owners had repair'd to the King for relief. Which, as in the General it suppos'd a Justice in such complaints, so it left a suspition of great hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships in the Methods of Redress; besides that the number of Captives was no small proof of the facility of Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>While the Lords were in the midst of this Examination, there was presented to the Committee, as it was receiv'd from Monsieur <hi>Courtin,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Ambassador, an Extract of a Letter from Monsieur <hi>Colbert</hi> to Monsieur <hi>Pompone,</hi> one of the <hi>French</hi> King's Secretaries, dated <hi>June</hi> 28th. 1676. in these Words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>FOr what concerns the Prizes, it would be a difficult mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to answer all the Cases contain'd in Monsieur <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi>'s Letter.</p>
                     <p>What I can say to it, is, That the Council for Marine Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs sits every day at St. <hi>Germaines.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That all Privateers and Reclaimers know it.</p>
                     <p>That Sir <hi>Ellis Leighton,</hi> nominated by the <hi>English</hi> Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sador, hath always notice of it, and is always present at it.</p>
                     <p>That not a week passes, but I give him two or three Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diences, and oftentimes I send for him on purpose.</p>
                     <p>That his Reasons are all read, reported and committed; as likewise are all Petitions of Reclaimers, and I shall tell you more, I acquaint him with the Reasons upon which Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is given.</p>
                     <p>In giving Judgment, all Vessels which have any Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of being <hi>English</hi> are releas'd, and very often, and almost always; though we are satisfied that the Ships are <hi>Dutch,</hi> yet they are releas'd because there is some appearance of their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55190:14"/>being <hi>English,</hi> and every thing is judg'd favourable for that Nation. And it is no less true that all Ships that are taken are <hi>Dutch</hi> Built, that they never were in <hi>England,</hi> that the Masters and all the Equipage are <hi>Dutch,</hi> that the Cockets are for Persons unknown, and which are not oft-times so much as nam'd; that they carry with them only some Sea Breifs from <hi>Waterford</hi> or some other Town of <hi>Ireland;</hi> that the whole Ships Company deposes, they were sent to <hi>Holland;</hi> that we have found on Board three or four Vessels, Bills of Accompt, by which it is seen that the <hi>English</hi> took two, three, and four <hi>per Cent,</hi> for owning Ships and though it is impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to avoid confiscating them, yet these are the Ships which make such a noise in <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To which the Lords of the Committee upon serious Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, by way of Answer represented to the King, That their Sentiments of the matter were quite different from what was pretended by the <hi>French;</hi> for that they understood that when the <hi>English</hi> Ships were carried into the Ports of <hi>France,</hi> many of the Mariners complain'd of ill Usage, and some of <hi>Torment,</hi> their Papers being seiz'd, and their <hi>Persons</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der restraint, till all the Examinations were ready prepar'd; and that then all their <hi>Writings</hi> were sent up to the Privy Council at St. <hi>Germaines,</hi> where judgment was definitively given, and seldom any reasons for the Condemnation men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd in the decree, and never any Appeal or Revision ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; and whether that were the Tenderness or the Justice pretended by the <hi>French,</hi> they could not tell: But they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd to the Ambassadour Monsieur <hi>Courtin</hi> himself, whether the Method of proceeding in <hi>England</hi> had not been quite otherwise; and therefore that the different Methods of Justice and Clemency in <hi>England,</hi> might have entitled His Majesty to a different acknowledgment, and more advantageous ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects from the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That as to the latter part of the Paper, it seem'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain very harsh Imputations upon the Trade of His Majesty's Subjects; and that only from some ill practices perhaps found out, general Rules were made, which having enter'd the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55190:15"/>Thoughts of some Eminent Ministers, that wonder'd that notwithstanding the frequent and multiply'd Recommendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Majesty for Justice, the event of the <hi>French</hi> Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als should prove so unfortunate; that if his Majesty would but cast his Eye upon the Causes annex'd, he would soon see.</p>
            <p>Whether, as it was imputed, all the Ships taken were <hi>Dutch</hi> Built.</p>
            <p>Whether they were all such as never were in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether all the Masters and Mariners were <hi>Dutch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether the Cockets were for Persons unknown, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes not nam'd.</p>
            <p>Whether in the whole List there was any more then one Ship from <hi>Waterford,</hi> any more than six from the rest of all <hi>Ireland,</hi> or so much as one from <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether it were credible that all the Ships Company should swear they were bound for <hi>Holland,</hi> when so many were taken coming from <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other side, His Majesty would find in the List how many were <hi>English</hi> Built, taken with <hi>English</hi> Colours, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Mariners, <hi>English</hi> Owners; some of them known to His Majesty, and to whom the best Papers His Majesty could sign, or the Treaties requir'd were given all in vain.</p>
            <p>So that if the Case were in the General quite different from what in the General is represented, they hop'd it was no crime for His Majesty's Subjects to make some noise in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> when they are Damnified, and see their Goods taken from them by Violence, and that Violence rather justifi'd than redress'd by Law.</p>
            <p>Wherefore considering that the Root of all these Disorders arose from the Violence and Rapine of the <hi>French</hi> Capers, who were to be lookt upon as Disturbers of the Publick Quiet, and Enemies of the Good Friendship between the two Crowns; they were humbly of Opinion that His <hi>Majesty</hi> had just Occasion from the injuries past, and those which were then depending, and which every day increas'd, to make a serious Representation of all to the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King, and not only to press for some better Method of repairing the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55190:15"/>Greivances mentioned, but to insist upon the calling in of all the <hi>French</hi> Privateers; or else that His Majesty ought to doe right, and give defence to his Subjects, from all the insolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which they so frequently met with. This was sign'd.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anglisey</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bath</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Craven</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. Ernle</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Finch</hi> C.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bridgewater</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>H. Coventry</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>G. Carteret</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I might here add the List it self, by which it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that, contrary to Monsieur <hi>Colbert</hi>'s Allegations, the Ships so taken were all either <hi>English</hi> Built, or Foreigners made Free, fraighted by <hi>English</hi> Merchants, own'd by <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Men, and mann'd with <hi>English,</hi> with Cockets and Bills of Lading to <hi>English.</hi> But 'tis sufficient for me to shew, that the Ministers and the Masters are <hi>Christians</hi> alike, <hi>Plunderers</hi> and <hi>Robbers,</hi> not only of Imperial Territories and Royal Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, but <hi>Beasts</hi> of Prey, that turn the Seas into a Desart, to gorge their voracious Appetites upon the Estates of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Persons; and that upon the Account their <hi>Injustice</hi> and <hi>Rapines</hi> so wickedly and unjustly practised upon the People of <hi>England,</hi> no Nation under Heaven can have reasons more allowable on their side to justifie a War with <hi>France,</hi> than <hi>England</hi> has, for the many <hi>Dishonours, Injuries,</hi> and <hi>Affronts</hi> so ungratefully done us, in recompence of all the Kindness and great Services done them from time to time.</p>
            <p>For what greater kindness could there be, than to furnish the <hi>Aspiring Monarch</hi> with a continually recruited body of Ten Thousand of our <hi>English</hi> Youth, whose daring Bravery and Courage made oftentimes a Rape upon Victory it self, to force her on his side, and rescu'd once his whole Army from destruction; when in consternation, and pursu'd by the Imperalists, upon the fall of <hi>Turenne?</hi> Yet when by the importunity of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> they were recall'd out of his service, instead of fairly dismissing them, well pay'd, for <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk</hi> or <hi>Calais,</hi> from thence to cross over for <hi>Dover,</hi> which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55190:16"/>was their direct Way; they were sent through <hi>Burgundy,</hi> through <hi>Liomois,</hi> and so through the Provinces that lead to the Ports of <hi>Guyenne,</hi> that so the <hi>French</hi> might have time to debauch the Officers and Soldiers. In short, the Soldiers who since their being in <hi>France,</hi> had been accustom'd to drink Wine, finding themselves in a Country where it was almost as plentifull as Water, would not cross the Sea to go home and drink Beer, but took pay under the Captains of the <hi>French</hi> Army in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> who were for that purpose posted in their way. As for such of the Officers as had nothing to lose in their own Country, they were likewise debauch'd after the same manner, and dispers'd at the same time in the Regiment of <hi>Fustenburgh,</hi> which was in the Garrison of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pignan:</hi> So that when the <hi>English</hi> arriv'd at the Place where they were to Embark, they were not the Tenth of what they should have been, had <hi>France</hi> dealt faithfully in the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness.</p>
            <p>Thus we have run through the Treacheries and Infidelities of the <hi>French</hi> in reference to <hi>England.</hi> There is no Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but much more might have been said; however, here is enough to shew that there can be no safety in the friendship of a Prince, who makes it his study to be injurious in all his Actions, and faithless in all his Promises: <hi>Mendaciis &amp; falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis tanquam praeclaris Artibus gaudens.</hi> But such is the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of that pernicious Vice, desire of too much Glory, that it constrains a Man to be perfidious, as it was said of <hi>Cneus Domitius; Nimiae Gloriae Cupiditas perfidum existere coegit.</hi> And this was a Maxim among the Ancients, that Fidelity, like the Soul, when it has once left a Man, never returns again: And therefore with such a one, <hi>Bellum suspecta Pace tutius est.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us look Abroad, where we shall find the Most <hi>Christian</hi> of Princes, stradling over <hi>Violations</hi> of <hi>Oaths</hi> by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Name, call'd <hi>Perjuries,</hi> and all the Laws and Bounds of Justice which God and Man have provided against the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undations of Violence, to grasp the Universal Monarchy of <hi>Europe.</hi> There you shall find him Invading, Burning, Spoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55190:16"/>Plundring, Sacking, and Depopulating the Territories and Dominions of his Peaceable <hi>Christian</hi> Neighbours, <hi>hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> out his way through the Bowels of Christendom to the Imperial Throne; and all this under <hi>Claims</hi> and <hi>Pretensions,</hi> abjur'd by all the most Solemn Renunciations that Religion could invent. Yet in Re-vindication of those Claims and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>assumed Rights so religiously renounc'd, like another <hi>Parenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus abominatus Hannibal,</hi> filling all with <hi>Bloud, Massacre</hi> and <hi>Devastation</hi> to Tyrannize over wasted Ruines, Cities laid Desolate, and desart Mountains, rather than not to Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannize at all. Where he could not enter with his Sword, he open'd a Passage with his <hi>Gold</hi> for subservient Treachery, and the <hi>Foundations</hi> of future Mischief into the Courts of most of the Princes of <hi>Europe;</hi> deflouring the Fidelity of their Counsellers, and <hi>ravishing</hi> the Allegiance of their most Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Intimates, as if there had been a kind of Omnipotency in the Power of <hi>France</hi> to make Treachery and Falshood Ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitary.</p>
            <p>Perhaps this may be thought a little too severe; but this is not a time to Complement the <hi>Publick Enemy</hi> of Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. This is a Season to speak out, since the wellfare of <hi>England</hi> is involv'd in the Common Fate of <hi>Europe.</hi> It is the Business of <hi>England</hi> to evidence how the <hi>French</hi> have violated the Law of Nations, which is common to all; and how they have labour'd to introduce such <hi>Maxims</hi> into the World, as would destroy even the whole commerce of Mankind, and render Humane Societies no less Dangerous than a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Tygers, Bears,</hi> and <hi>Lyons.</hi> Nor is <hi>England</hi> less con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to defend the Publick Faith of Treaties against the crafty Elusions and Quaint Evasions of the <hi>French,</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move out of the sight of Christendom such Scandalous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, which, by consequences no less fatal than unavoidable, would expose the Weakest to the Predominant Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of the strongest, and establish Force, the Grand Arbitrator of all the Proceedings and Affairs of the World. It is the Business of <hi>England,</hi> in confederacy with Foreign Princes for the General Wellfare of Christendom, to betake Her self to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55190:17"/>such means and courses, as may put a stop to a rapid Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent against the Impetuosity, of which no Ties of Treaty, Marriage, Oaths, Bloud, Kindred, Friendship, or Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scension, can be Mounds and Bulwarks strong enough to keep it within its Chanel. It is the Business of <hi>England,</hi> as far as in Her lies, to defend the common Interest of all Princes and States against a Prodigious Design; which for its Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, has nothing but an Exorbitant desire of Conquest; no other End, than only Dominion; no other Means, but force of Arms and Treacherous Policy; nor any other Bounds, but what Chance and Fortune will be pleas'd to prescribe. Lastly, It is not only the Business, but also for the Glory of <hi>England</hi> at this time, to recover Her former <hi>Grandeur;</hi> and as She was wont to doe, so at this time to decide the Fortune of <hi>Europe,</hi> and pronounce the Sentence either of Her Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or Slavery: For between these two, there is no Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um to be expected, nor Peace to be secur'd. <hi>England</hi> for a long time has lain in a profound Lethargy, and therefore it is high time for Her now to awake, and put Her helping hand to prevent the Misfortunes and Calamities to which all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> is expos'd by the prevailing Tyrannies and Oppression of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are then in the next place to consider how like a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King has dealt with the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> his Brother, His Friend, and Allie, after a Peace the most Solemnly concluded and ratified, after the most Sacred man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that could be imagin'd. Certainly the Calamities, the Miseries, the Murthers, Rapines and Devastations, and Innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Impieties that attend on War, are so disagreeable from the Principles of <hi>Christian</hi> Religion, that nothing ought to be more Seriously, more Moderately, and more Warily consider'd than the Justice of undertaking it: And therefore said <hi>Herennius,</hi> Captain of the <hi>Samnites,</hi> having enter'd into a War against the <hi>Romans,</hi> after all that could be done to procure Peace, <hi>Rerum humanarum maximum Momentum est, quam propitiis, quam adversis agant diis.</hi> Nor did he justifie the War upon any other grounds, than that his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55190:17"/>were constrain'd to it, and had no other hope but in their Arms. <hi>Justum est Bellum, Samnites, quibus necessari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; pia Arma, quibus nulla nisi in Armis relinquitur spes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans,</hi> though too blame perhaps in the <hi>Samnite</hi> War, (for which they dearly paid, and well it might be wish'd the <hi>French</hi> might pay as dearly for what they have done,) generally never enter'd into a War, but they set forth the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of their Resentment, which for the most part was in revenge of their Allies, or to succour their Friends and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates. Thus the first <hi>Punick</hi> War was to succour <hi>Messana</hi> in <hi>Sicily,</hi> besieg'd by the <hi>Carthaginians.</hi> The second in revenge of <hi>Saguntum,</hi> sack'd by <hi>Hannibal,</hi> contrary to the League between the two Common-wealths. And the third also for Reasons of the same Nature: And so cautious they were to avoid the Scandal of being thought to make War, merely out of an Ambitious desire to extend their Dominions, that after they had vanquish'd and reduc'd the <hi>Rhodians,</hi> who had taken part with <hi>Perseus</hi> in the <hi>Macedonian</hi> War, they let them go unpunish'd: <hi>Ne quis divitiarum magis quam injuriae Bellum incoeptum diceret.</hi> And the same Author says, that in all the <hi>Punick</hi> Wars, after the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> had committed many nefarious Acts and Breaches of Faith to their Detriment, they never took any occasion to doe the like; <hi>Magis quod se dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num foret, quam quod in illos jure fieri posset quaerebant:</hi> So that occasions of enlarging their Dominions were rather of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd than sought for by that Victorious Common-wealth. And it is observable, that the Ceremonies of denouncing War that were first instituted by <hi>Ancus Martius,</hi> the Heathen King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> were perform'd as Religiously, and with equal Soleminty to the Ceremonies of their Divine Worship. For when the <hi>Fecial</hi> came to the confines of the Country, against which the War was intended, <hi>Audi Jupiter,</hi> he cry'd; <hi>Audite Fines, Audiat Fas:</hi> Hear O <hi>Jupiter,</hi> Hear O ye Confines, hear Right and Justice: <hi>I am the Publick Messenger of the People of</hi> Rome, <hi>and come a Fecial, justly and piously sent, and let Faith be given to my Words.</hi> After that, having made his demands, he again calls <hi>Jupiter</hi> to Witness, and thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55190:18"/>
               <hi>Si ego injuste, impieque illos homines illasque res dedier Nuncio Populi Romani Exposco, tum Patriae Compotem me nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam sinas esse;</hi> if satisfaction were not given by the Prince or People to whom he was thus sent within three and thirty days, the <hi>Fecial</hi> return'd again, and denounc'd War after this manner. <hi>Audi Jupiter, &amp; tu Juno, Quirine, Diique om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes coelestes vosque terrestres, vosque inferni audite; Ego vos testor Populum istum injustum esse, neque jus persolvere,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus the more noble <hi>Heathen Romans,</hi> before they invaded the Borders of their Enemies, invok'd the Gods to Witness the Justice of their Cause, and the Wrongs and Injuries of those that had incens'd them to take Arms. On the other side, the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King not regarding either God or Man, unexpected, unprovok'd, nay, after he had given as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surances that he had no such design in his thoughts, <hi>thunder'd</hi> into his Neighbours Territories, under the Protection of League and Amity; and like a sudden Tempest, with Sword and Fire, levels all before him.</p>
            <q>Burgundos Fraude Petivit</q>
            <p>Such an Ignoble and Unprincelike way of entring into Hostility, as looks more like Robbing upon the High-way, than a generous Method of War: For that it was a <hi>base</hi> and <hi>ignominious</hi> surprizal against the Faith and Honour of a King, besides the Breach of Treaty is apparent from two Circumstances; the one that pass'd at <hi>Paris</hi> between the <hi>French</hi> King himself, and the Marquess <hi>De la Fuente</hi> Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Ambassadour from <hi>Spain,</hi> who being upon his return into <hi>Spain</hi> upon the Death of the Old King, and not a little apprehensive and jealous, that the vast Preparations made in <hi>France,</hi> were intended against the Queen and the Young Prince, was very importunate with his Most <hi>Christian</hi> Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, to give some new and greater Assurances to the Queen of <hi>Spain,</hi> of the reality and sincerity of his Intentions, though it were but only to quiet and settle her mind, against all the contrary Advices she receiv'd from all Parts. Upon which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55190:18"/>the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King with all possible Asseverations en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd his Faith and Royal Word to the Queen, in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of her Ambassadour, that he would religiously keep the Peace, and continue a most faithfull Friendship both to Her and her Son.</p>
            <p>Another circumstance was that of the Archbishop of <hi>Ambrun,</hi> who, after the <hi>French</hi> Army was already in the Field, and had possess'd <hi>Charleroy,</hi> some four or five days before the News of it came to <hi>Madrid,</hi> protested and vow'd in <hi>Verbo Sacerdotis,</hi> and by all that was Sacred among the Roman Catholicks, that his Master intended nothing less than what was reported of him, and that he would never break with the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> nor invade his Dominions as long as he was under Age. And when the March of the <hi>French</hi> Army, and the Hostilities which they committed, so little agreed with the Promises of the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King; answer was made that it was no Breach, but only a taking Possession of what belong'd to him: But the only way to surprize Men, is to take them unprovided; and the only way to take them unprovided, is to swear with all the Asseverations imaginable, that you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intend to doe them any harm. And this is one of the Most <hi>Christian</hi> Kings ways of making War upon his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, so far from giving them thirty three Days Notice of his coming, that he will hardly allow them thirty three Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes: But it is a meanness in a Prince instructed by so great a Tutor as <hi>Mazarine,</hi> to be a <hi>slave to his Word;</hi> for which reason <hi>Fides Gallica,</hi> is of late become <hi>Fides Punica,</hi> no sooner given but as soon broken.</p>
            <p>True it is that the <hi>French Academy</hi> has been long endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to refine their Language, by leaving off the use of some obsolete Words, by introducing others of a new Coyn, and enriching it with several quaint Expressions of a fresher Date; but how they could alter the signification of Words, and call <hi>War</hi> by the name of <hi>Peace,</hi> is a thing not easie to be understood: And therefore it were to be wish'd, they would explain to the World what they mean by the word <hi>Rupture,</hi> and how they can make a violent Invasion with Men and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55190:19"/>great Guns, to agree with the Observation of a Treaty, which forbid all manner of Attempts by armed Force, and was stipulated and contracted to no other end, but to prevent them: That they would explain which way it is possible for Peace to consist with the Fatal effects of War; and how it is to be imagin'd that wanting the Formality of a Herauld to Proclaim the Hostility, it should lose all its Terrors and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice; since most Men of ordinary Reason believe that to be a Rupture which opposes the very Essence and Being of the Peace, ranverses the very Foundations, and discomposes all the Harmony of it.</p>
            <p>Now the Causes that mov'd the two Crowns to make the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> League, <hi>were the desires of the Welfare, repose and ease of their Subjects.</hi> The effect was, <hi>to put an end to the many mischiefs of the War; to forget and extinguish all the Causes and Motives which occasion'd the War; and to establish a Sincere, Entire, and Durable Peace between the two Kings, and their Successors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which was ranvers'd by the first Invasion of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Netherlands,</hi> which disturb'd the Welfare and repose of the People, renew'd the Publick Calamities, and rekindl'd all the Causes of the past Wars.</p>
            <p>But to come to Particulars, the abandoning of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> was one of the essential Fundamentals of the Peace, without which it never could have been treated nor conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. In reference to this, the Sixtieth Article runs thus: <hi>For that His Majesty,</hi> meaning the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King, <hi>hath foreseen and fear'd, lest such an Engagement should be an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surmountable Obstruction to the conclusion of Peace; and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, reduce the two Kings to the necessity of a parpetual. War.</hi> And a little lower in the same Article, he goes on in these Words: <hi>Although in consideration of the Peace,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the absolute <hi>necessity his said Most</hi> Christian <hi>Majesty</hi> has been in to <hi>perpetuate the War by the Rupture of the</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Treaty, <hi>which His Majesty found to be unavoidable,</hi> in case he would <hi>have any longer insisted upon</hi> prevailing in that <hi>affair with His Catholick Majesty,</hi> to have obtain'd <hi>other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, than such as he offer'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:55190:19"/>
            <p>In the second place, it is plain that the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> to shew how resolv'd he was that <hi>France</hi> should abandon <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> rejected the <hi>French</hi> King's offering, besides the places he was bound to restore by the present Treaty to his Catholick Majesty; all the rest of the Places and Conquests, generally made by his Arms, during the preceding War, provided that the Affairs of the Kingdom of <hi>Portugal</hi> might be left in the same condition as they were then, as by another part of the same Article it appears: So that when nothing else would doe, it was by the same Article concluded and promised as follows:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majesty will no farther meddle with that Affair, and obliges and engages Himself, and promises upon his Honour, and upon the Word of a King, for Himself and his Successors, not to give into the said Kingdom of</hi> Portugal, <hi>either in General, or to any Persons in particular, of what Dignity, State, Condition, or Quality soever they be, now or hereafter, any Help or Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence, Publick or Secret, Directly or Indirectly, of Men, Arms, Ammunition, Victuals, Ships, or Money, upon any pretence or any other thing whatever, either by Land or Sea, or in any other manner: As also, not to suffer that any Levies of Men be made in any parts of his Kingdom or Dominions; nor to grant Passage to any that may come from other States, to the Assistence of the said Kingdom of</hi> Portugal.</p>
            <p>One would think that nothing could have been more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentickly expressed, or in terms more clear or more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, beyond the power of <hi>Nicety</hi> to find a flaw, or to make any other interpretation of the words, contrary to the sense and meaning of the Parties at that time. And yet the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King found out a way to fail in all the Points, and all the circumstances of his Promise: For notwithstanding his <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>the Word of a King,</hi> before the Treaty was sign'd, Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> sent privately the Marquess of <hi>Cheases</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Portugal,</hi> to assure them, that tho' in order to the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the Treaty then on foot with <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> were forc'd to leave them out, and to engage not to assist them; yet, whatever they promis'd, they would never forsake them,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55190:20"/>but would still protect them against <hi>Spain,</hi> as they had done before: And they kept their word with <hi>Portugal,</hi> because it was to the prejudice of <hi>Spain.</hi> To which purpose, the Peace was no sooner concluded, but they suffer'd several Bands of Soldiers secretly to convey themselves into <hi>Portugal;</hi> which being complain'd of by the Marquess <hi>De la Fuente,</hi> such was the <hi>Punic</hi> Faith of <hi>France,</hi> that openly they sent Publick Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the Governours of their Ports, not to suffer any Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to embark for <hi>Portugal,</hi> but underhand gave them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Orders to let them pass by way of connivance. Soon after M. <hi>Turenne</hi> made publick levies of Men, for the relief of <hi>Portugal,</hi> which the <hi>Spanish</hi> Ambassador representing to the Council of <hi>France,</hi> receiv'd a cold and scornfull answer, that it was a particular Act of Marshall <hi>Turenne,</hi> wherein the Court was no way concern'd: Nor did the <hi>French</hi> cease to furnish the <hi>Portuguieses</hi> with Corn, and all sorts of War-like Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and Provision. Moreover, Letters were intercepted by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> by which they were ascertain'd, that all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long after the Peace was concluded, the <hi>French</hi> fomented and encourag'd the obstinacy of the <hi>Portuguieses,</hi> and diverted them from accepting the advantageous conditions that were offer'd them, by animating them with the hopes of potent Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours, not only for their own defence, but also to carry an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensive War into the heart of <hi>Spain.</hi> Other Letters were like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise intercepted, Written from the Arch Bishop of <hi>Ambrun,</hi> and Monsieur <hi>Lienne</hi> confirming the continual correspondence which was between them in favour of the <hi>Portugals:</hi> Nor was this all, for the D. of <hi>B.</hi> was presently after the Treaty, sent to lie with the <hi>French</hi> Fleet upon the Coast of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and stay'd there a whole Summer to secure the coming and landing of Provisions and Ammunition, of which the <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guieses</hi> were then in extream want; and this at the same time that the <hi>French</hi> offer'd to mediate an Accomodation between <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugal.</hi> Nor was it long after the conclusion of the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Treaty, that Monsieur <hi>Colbert</hi> made several Voyages into <hi>Portugal,</hi> to encourage them against the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and to enter into secret Alliance with them: And sometime after the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55190:20"/>
               <hi>Spaniards</hi> took a <hi>French</hi> Vessel, wherein was found an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the succours which <hi>France</hi> had sent from time to time into that Kindom; by which it appear'd, that <hi>France</hi> had paid at her own expence a standing Army in <hi>Portugal,</hi> to support a War against <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to compleat her Persidy, at length she concluded a League offensive with that Kingdom, of which these were the principal Conditions: <hi>That they would be the Friends of each others Friends, and Enemies of each others Enemies,</hi> England <hi>only excepted: That</hi> France <hi>should furnish them with us many Men, as should be necessary to carry an offensive War into</hi> Spain, <hi>both by Sea and Land, and should advance by way of Loan, the one half of the Pay for the maintenance of the</hi> Auxiliary <hi>Troops. That</hi> France <hi>moreover should pay them every Year by way of Loan, the summ of</hi> 300000 <hi>Crowns, and that all the Ports which should be taken from the</hi> Spaniards <hi>upon either Sea, should be put into the hands of the</hi> French, <hi>and that they should not treat either of Truce or League without joynt consent. This League to continue Ten Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By so many several Instances, let all the World be judges how little <hi>credit</hi> there is to be given to the <hi>Punic Faith</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> or what any other Prince can expect from his <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> or his <hi>Promises</hi> in any matter whatsoever; who thus <hi>foully forfeited</hi> such a most Solemn Engagement to the Crown of <hi>Spain.</hi> For that a Treaty carry'd on between two Princes in order to a Marriage, which is one of the most Solemn Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations that can be handled among Men, and <hi>confirm'd</hi> by an <hi>Oath, sanctifi'd</hi> with all the most sacred Mysteries of Christian Religion, for a punctual obligation of performance, should be thus inhumanly <hi>violated,</hi> is not to be parallell'd by any Example or Instance in History.</p>
            <p>That noble example of the Roman Consuls, who bid <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> not to fear, the Publick Faith secur'd him, is a thing of late unknown in <hi>France,</hi> where there is no security or trust in the Honour or Royal Promise of the Prince. For his truth to <hi>Portugal</hi> was only self-interest, to support the <hi>Portuguieses</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Spain,</hi> as formerly the <hi>French</hi> were wont to league
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55190:21"/>with <hi>Scotland</hi> against <hi>England;</hi> so that whether the Character of <hi>Amurath</hi> the first, Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who is said to have been <hi>Homo fallax, qui datam fidem ex opportunitate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferendi imprimis metiebatur, bello &amp; pace simulato Egregius,</hi> may not fitly be apply'd to the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King, is left for them to determine who have felt the smart of his <hi>broken Leagues;</hi> which brings us to the second Breach of the <hi>Pyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naean</hi> Treaty. It is said, and acknowledg'd by the <hi>Plenipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiaries</hi> in 33d. Article of that Treaty, that the particular Captiulation of Marriage between the <hi>French</hi> King and the Eldest Daughter of <hi>Spain,</hi> bearing date with the General Treaty, was of the same force and vigor with the Treaty of Peace, as being the chiefest part thereof, and the most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, as well as the greatest and most precious Earnest of the security of its Duration.</p>
            <p>The Queen Mother of <hi>France,</hi> and Aunt to the <hi>Infanta,</hi> desiring nothing more than the happy and suitable Union of two Persons that were so dear in her Affection, to remove all impediments, and dispell the doubts and scruples of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> Counsel; found out an expedient, that by the contract of Marriage, the <hi>Infanta</hi> should absolutely renounce all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Right or Claim, which she might for ever have to the whole, or any parts of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Succession under any Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or Title whatever, to the end the <hi>Spanish</hi> Monarchy might in no case be liable, either to Foreign Subjection, or to be Dismember'd: And they were more inclinable on both sides to this expedient, because the way had been open'd for them before by the Example of the Queen-Mother, whose Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation was of the same Nature with the <hi>Pyrenaean,</hi> both in form and substance, and grounded upon the same incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the two Successions.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Spain</hi> believing the same sincerity in others as in himself, hearken'd to the offer, and thought that with such a precaution he might reconcile the <hi>Spanish</hi> Law with the <hi>Salique,</hi> and fully secure the Liberty of his Subjects. <hi>France</hi> on the other side acknowledg'd the thing to be <hi>just</hi> and <hi>usual,</hi> and freely consented to it, for the sake of the general good
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55190:21"/>that should result from such a Peace, and confirm him in the possession of so many conquests. Thereupon the Instrument was drawn up by consent, and the <hi>French</hi> King oblig'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to ratifie it.</p>
            <p>Whence it is plain, that the <hi>Renunciation</hi> was an essential Member of the Peace, the very <hi>Soul</hi> and an inseparable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the <hi>Treaty</hi> of <hi>Marriage,</hi> without which it never had been projected nor concluded, and consequently neither the Treaty of Peace.</p>
            <p>Then again, that it was no private Act, but a Law and Pragmatick Sanction establish'd by joynt consent of the two Crowns, is as clear from the words of the Act it self; <hi>And in the fifth and sixth Articles of the said Treaty, it has been decreed and resolv'd by joynt consent,</hi> that is to say, of the two Kings; <hi>and with one will, after serious consideration,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that both my self, and the Children which God shall give me by this Marriage, are and shall remain uncapable, disabl'd, and abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely excluded from any right or hope to succeed in any of the Kingdoms, States, Signiories,</hi> &amp;c. And a little lower, conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scending to this with the joint desire and earnest wishes of their Subjects, Vassals, and Natives, who desire <hi>that it may have the force and vigour of a Law and Pragmatick Sanction, and that it may be receiv'd and observ'd as such;</hi> and some lines low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the following Section, are added these words: <hi>And it shall be decreed, by joynt consent, that it is their Majesties Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, that this Act shall have the force and vigour of a Law E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablish'd in favour of their Kingdoms, and the publick interests of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A little above the three moving causes are specifi'd; <hi>And in regard it concerns the Publick State of both Crowns, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so large, they may never come to be united together, and to prevent all occasions that may happen of joyning them,</hi> &amp;c. which is more fully explain'd two Pages lower. <hi>And having joyntly regard to the Publick and Common Good of the Kingdoms,</hi> which God has entrusted him with, which together with these be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> are equally interested in this; that the <hi>Grandeur</hi> and <hi>Majesty</hi> which they have upheld
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55190:22"/>and maintain'd for so many Years together; with so much Happiness and Glory to the renown of their Kings, may not be diminish'd nor fall to decay, as of necessity they will diminish and fall, if by the means and cause of this <hi>Marriage,</hi> they shall happen to unite and be joyn'd together in any one of the Children and Successors; the ill consequences whereof would cause such discontents and afflictions to the Subjects, as ought to be consider'd: Then the causes of the Renunciation are express'd to be the <hi>publick good</hi> of the Kingdoms, the preservation of the <hi>Grandeur,</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of their Majesties; to prevent the discontents of the People, and the Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences which might otherwise arise, and to facilitate for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Marriages between the Children and Successors of the two Princes. All which causes being in their own nature <hi>unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable,</hi> and of necessity absolute, could not be fasten'd upon any particular Act, nor limited to any restrictive conditions.</p>
            <p>This League therefore thus grounded upon these Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, were such Limitations and bounds to a Person aspiring to the Universal Monarchy of <hi>Europe,</hi> as were not to be fenced in with the common Ties and restraints of <hi>Oaths</hi> and Treaties. And therefore so soon as the Old King of <hi>Spain</hi> was <hi>dead,</hi> the <hi>French Lawyers,</hi> well understanding the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of their Sovereign, and preferring the little <hi>Quirks</hi> of <hi>Law</hi> before the <hi>Publick Faith,</hi> started up a claim for their King in the right and behalf of his Wife the <hi>Infanta,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing her <hi>Solemn Renunciation,</hi> which was made a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the body of the Treaty, and as sacredly sworn to by the <hi>French</hi> King himself; pretending that a great part of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Low Countries was devolv'd to him in her Right by the Municipal Laws, and Local Customs of those Countries. Whereas it is a thing well known, that when Sovereign Princes enter into Treaties (which are indeed the true and only Laws between Monarchs) they are regulated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd according to the Law of Nations common to all; and being so to be understood, it is an idle thing for <hi>Civilians</hi> to imagin, that a consideration of Laws Municipal, or customs belonging to any particlar Country, under the Dominion of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55190:22"/>either of the Treating Princes, can be admitted to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing of a Treaty, or the depriving either of the Parties of the Benefit and Security which he has thereby.</p>
            <p>But notwithstanding the <hi>Renunciation</hi> was so carefully Penn'd, as if a whole Grand Council of <hi>Civil Lawyers</hi> had been call'd to out-doe all former Terms and expressions us'd in such Contracts, and to find out new binding Clauses; to prevent all possibility of Evasion, the <hi>French</hi> King was more easily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to believe that his own great <hi>Cannon-Law</hi> was above all other <hi>Law,</hi> and more consentaneous to his Reason and his Designs; and therefore against the very sense and end of the <hi>Renunciation,</hi> under the slight pretence of a <hi>Non-Entity,</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took himself to force and violence, and with a powerfull Army fell on a sudden upon <hi>Flanders,</hi> and other parts of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Territories, with such an Inundation of War, that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible for the unprovided <hi>Spaniard</hi> to resist him; more espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, after such deep Asseverations, that all his vast Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations were no way intended against the <hi>Spanish</hi> Dominions.</p>
            <p>These prosperous successes occasioned the <hi>Triple League,</hi> which put a stop to the <hi>French</hi> Career, and brought on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Treaty,</hi> which was manag'd at <hi>Aken,</hi> or <hi>Aix la Chappelle,</hi> in order to a new Agreement between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> The Observation of which affords us another instance of that ye call <hi>French Fidelity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this Treaty the <hi>French</hi> King was to remain possess'd of <hi>Charleroy, Binch, Athe, Doway,</hi> the Fort of <hi>Scarp, Turnay, Oude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, Lille, Armentiers, Courtray, Bergues,</hi> and <hi>Turnes,</hi> and all their <hi>Bayliwicks,</hi> &amp;c. and restore to the King of <hi>Spain</hi> the County of <hi>Burgundy</hi> together with <hi>Alost.</hi> And to this <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> all the Princes of <hi>Christendom</hi> were invited to give the two Kings their <hi>Promises</hi> and <hi>Engagements</hi> of <hi>Warranty,</hi> as to all the Contents of the <hi>Treaty.</hi> And by another Article of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it was accorded, that whatever should on the day of the <hi>Ratification</hi> of the <hi>Peace</hi> be found upon the <hi>Lands</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> should appertain to Her, and that whatever in like manner should be found upon the <hi>Lands</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> should appertain to the Crown of <hi>Spain;</hi> but, as if it were an impossibility for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55190:23"/>
               <hi>France</hi> to keep her word, the Most <hi>Christian</hi> Prince designing to make his Advantage of this Article, before the Ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on came, caus'd the <hi>Ax</hi> to be set to a <hi>Wood</hi> of <hi>Overgrown Trees,</hi> which was upon the <hi>Lands</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> and having fell'd the Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, transported it into his own Dominions, that when the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification</hi> should come, he might have an excuse for what he had done.</p>
            <p>In like manner, though he were to restore all <hi>Burgundy</hi> by the <hi>Articles</hi> of this <hi>Treaty</hi> without reservation, and though he were Sworn upon the Cross, the Holy Evangelists, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Mass, and upon his Honour, fully, really, and <hi>bona fide</hi> to observe and accomplish all the contents of the Articles: yet he both dismantl'd the strong Holds and Places of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, carryed away all the Ammunitions and Warlike Provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and would have destroyed the Rich Salt Pits of that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince,</hi> but for the powerfull Interposition of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor could this Treaty of <hi>Aix,</hi> so religiously sworn to tie up the <hi>French</hi> King from exacting heavy Contributions from the Duchess of <hi>Lymburgh</hi> and <hi>Luxenburgh,</hi> from laying new claims to some Towns as important as any of those that had been granted him by the Peace; nor from confiscating the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states of the Subjects of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> that refus'd to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swear their Allegiance, not sparing the Royal House of <hi>Mary Mont.</hi> And as if these Infractions and Incroachments had not been sufficient, they forc'd their way with great Quantities of Merchandize through the <hi>Spanish</hi> Territories, without paying Customs, and not long after enveavour'd to surprize the Town of <hi>Hainault.</hi> And in short, they did whatever they pleas'd, plunder'd even the most sacred Places, and acted without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morce or pitty, whatever can be imagined by insolent and unconscionable Men.</p>
            <p>This perfidious dealing of <hi>France</hi> with <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> spreading over <hi>Europe</hi> like a Gangrene, as it prov'd extreamly prejudicial to some, so it became no less pernicious to others of the <hi>Europaean</hi> Princes.</p>
            <p>Among the rest, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> by the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:55190:23"/>Treaty, was to be restor'd to his Dukedom of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> with all the Places and towns which he had possessed in the Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks of <hi>Mets, Tool,</hi> and <hi>Verdun.</hi> But <hi>France,</hi> after the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the other Articles of that Peace, delay'd as long as she could the performance of that part which related to the Duke, and still refus'd to restore him to his Country, till she had made him condescend to another <hi>Treaty</hi> with her, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he was constrain'd to part with several other considerable Places, besides what had been granted to him by the <hi>General Peace.</hi> Nor would that Usurpation satisfie her voracious Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite; for that after a Year and an half of an unsettl'd Posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, during which time, under several unjust pretences, new quarrells were every day pick'd with him, till she forc'd him with a considerable Army, to surrender into her hands his Town of <hi>Marsul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was it long after before the <hi>French</hi> again compell'd him to sign a new <hi>Treaty,</hi> still more disadvantageous than the two former; nor coudl he then, as little as before, have any quiet Enjoyment of that little they had left him, till they had worm'd him out of all. For every day the <hi>French</hi> encroached upon his <hi>Jurisdiction,</hi> the Liberties of his <hi>Territories,</hi> and his <hi>Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> it self: He laid most <hi>Enormous Taxes</hi> upon the Duke's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; he constrain'd him to disband his <hi>Forces,</hi> and then to raise new <hi>Men</hi> again, as the Most <hi>Christian</hi> Usurper thought fit. He was kept from revenging his own Quarrels, to take part in that of others, all his Enemies were let loose against him, to stop the progress of his Armies, as soon as he had gain'd the least Advantage. And in few Words, the Noble Duke, who deserv'd a much better <hi>Treatment,</hi> was all that while rather a <hi>Vassal</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> than a <hi>Sovereign Prince.</hi> Neither would this satisfie the Ambition of the <hi>French</hi> King, who fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by many circumstances how highly the Duke resented such <hi>Despotick Ʋsage,</hi> he sent one of his Generals to surprize and seize his <hi>Person,</hi> and to bring him either dead or alive. A new <hi>French Mode</hi> of dealing with Sovereign Princes, not known in the more generous Climates of <hi>Europe,</hi> and which may give us some Hopes of seeing the <hi>Northern</hi> part of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55190:24"/>World govern'd by <hi>Basha</hi>'s as well as the <hi>Eastern.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 'tis an infallible <hi>Maxim,</hi> that every Prince dispossess'd of his Estate, may hold for certain there will be nothing omitted on the Usurper's part, or Conquerer in Possession, to ruin him if possible, and all his Generation. Therefore 'tis not strange that the <hi>French</hi> King should leave no Stone unturn'd for the Destruction of His Highness of <hi>Lorrain:</hi> From hence it was, that the <hi>Imperial Governour</hi> of <hi>Philipsburgh,</hi> the same who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards basely and cowardly surrender'd up that Garrison to <hi>Crequi,</hi> so notoriously and openly as he did, attempted the Destruction of that Prince, by a <hi>Trap-door</hi> which he cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caus'd to be contriv'd for that purpose in the <hi>Bridge</hi> of that Place; through which the Duke, not dreaming of any such <hi>French</hi> Treachery so near him, fell head-long to the Bottom of the <hi>Ditch.</hi> For may it not be justly inferr'd, that this <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> had capitulated and agreed with some Christian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of <hi>France,</hi> to execute so greatfull a peice of <hi>Treason,</hi> more especially, since it was by the Power of the Favourers of <hi>France</hi> at <hi>Vienna,</hi> that the <hi>Traitors</hi> escap'd altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punish'd.</p>
            <p>And now we are come to <hi>Vienna,</hi> it will not be amiss to take a short view of the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King's behaviour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Emperor, where he will be found nothing chang'd either in his <hi>Morals</hi> or his <hi>Politicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the occasion that ever his <hi>Imperial Majesty</hi> gave the <hi>French</hi> King, to make such Bloudy Wars upon Him, there is no body that can tell of any: Nor is it probable that a Prince so good Natur'd, so Piously inclin'd, so much given to Repose, and Peace, and so averse from contending with his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or making War upon his Inferiours, as he is said to be, should be an <hi>Aggressor:</hi> But all the World knows that it has been long the <hi>Ambition</hi> of <hi>France</hi> to grasp in his hands the Universal <hi>Monarchy</hi> of the fourth part of the <hi>Habitable Earth;</hi> and this is that which makes the <hi>French</hi> King seek Occasions of Publick Universal Disturbance, and the better to succeed, to leave nothing unattempted that force or fraud can procure. It is no Quarrel between <hi>Nations,</hi> bearing enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55190:24"/>to one <hi>another,</hi> neither is it in revenge of Injuries recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but an impotent <hi>Rage</hi> and <hi>Lust</hi> of Empire in one Man, that has set all <hi>Europe</hi> together by the Ears; <hi>Delirat Ludovicus, plectitur Europa.</hi> One man is mad for the Empire, and that madness of one man sets all <hi>Europe</hi> in a <hi>Flame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for that the worst of Usurpers would be thought to have some glittering pretence for their <hi>Injustice,</hi> therefore it is that the <hi>French</hi> King makes it his business, to find out men of <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Cavil,</hi> to turmoil for Justifications of his illegal Actions; such men are easily found, and the Temptations of Gold makes them no less sedulous to gratifie the <hi>Jupiter</hi> that commands the Golden Showres; so that if they can but find him a Pretence of Claim, he'll find Armies and Bombs to make it good. Under the warmth of such Golden Encouragements was Hatch'd that Elaborate <hi>Peice,</hi> Entitled, <hi>The just Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of the King</hi> (meaning the <hi>French</hi> King) to <hi>Europe;</hi> wherein after the Author has laid it for a Foundation, that the <hi>Demesnes</hi> and Conquests of <hi>Kingdoms</hi> are always the <hi>Demesnes</hi> and Conquests of <hi>Sovereigns,</hi> and that the Conquests and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mesnes</hi> of Crowns cannot be ascertain'd or prescrib'd; he adds, <hi>That the greater part of</hi> Germany <hi>is the Patrimony and Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent inheritance of the</hi> French <hi>Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charlemaigne possess'd</hi> Germany <hi>not as Emperor, but as King of</hi> France. From which Doctrine it is evident, that his <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Majesty,</hi> nor indeed any Prince in <hi>Europe,</hi> can ever be safe, nor hope for any quiet, while the <hi>Ambition</hi> of <hi>France</hi> is in a condition to lay such a claim to their <hi>Dominions.</hi> More espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, since it is known by wofull experience, that the <hi>French</hi> King gives no other Reasons for his unjust <hi>Violences,</hi> nor cares to give any other than what the <hi>Lyon</hi> gave to the weaker <hi>Beasts;</hi> one part is his <hi>Right,</hi> as King of the <hi>Forest,</hi> another because he is able to <hi>subdue;</hi> the third he takes by <hi>Force,</hi> and for the <hi>rest,</hi> touch it who <hi>dares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Cunning, to set up a <hi>French</hi> Title is by the means of certain <hi>Scribes,</hi> as good as ever <hi>Granger,</hi> so dextrous at the strokes of their <hi>Pens,</hi> that they will imitate the obsolete <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thick</hi> Characters with that exactness, that you would swear
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:55190:25"/>they were Written above Five or Six Hundred Years agoe, and by that means, they will set up a <hi>Dependence</hi> from such a distance of time, that <hi>Beelzebub</hi> himself shall not be able to disprove it.</p>
            <p>Upon these Foundations it was, that as if he were dealing only with the <hi>Farmers</hi> of his <hi>Revenues,</hi> by a Publick <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> he erected a Sovereign Court at <hi>Mets,</hi> compos'd accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the custom of <hi>France,</hi> of a dozen of his Lawyers, who, by virtue of the King's Authority, and the Ministry of the <hi>Catchpoles</hi> of that clandestine Jurisdiction, summon before them all such <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> as are possess'd of any Territory which the King is pleas'd to call a <hi>Dependence</hi> upon any State, with which he has nothing to doe; and when no body appears to acknowledge the Jurisdiction of this <hi>Tyrannical</hi> and <hi>Ʋniversal Piepoudre,</hi> and to give them an account by what Right they possess what their Predecessors have for three or four Hundred Years peaceably enjoy'd; presently the Most <hi>Christian</hi> Prince makes his own Power his Judges, and his Army his Advo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cates, and immediately with <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Sword</hi> seizes upon the confiscated <hi>Dominion.</hi> And by virtue of such Pretensions as these, he <hi>claims</hi> and has <hi>possess;d</hi> himself of the Dukedom of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the Dutchy of <hi>Deux Ponts,</hi> and the best part of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satia,</hi> as being dependencies of the <hi>Bishopricks</hi> of <hi>Toul, Metz,</hi> and <hi>Verdun;</hi> and consequently must be united to the <hi>Demesnes</hi> of the Crown of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having then so clear a Title to the <hi>Empire,</hi> no wonder he pursues so <hi>dreadfully</hi> the recovery of his Right. And yet the true Mother of the Child could not endure to see the Bowels of her <hi>Infant</hi> ript up before her Eyes; no, nor can we believe the Most <hi>Christian</hi> Prince to be the Hereditary Father of those Countries, which, in detestation of all Compassion, he so inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly <hi>ransacks</hi> and <hi>depopulates;</hi> being then a Spurious Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, disown'd by the <hi>Legitimate Parents</hi> of all true Titles, <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> which only fraud and force could make good. Of both how dreadfully, and how too successfully the <hi>Ambitious Monarch</hi> has made use in asserting his illegal claims, all <hi>Europe</hi> can too sadly testifie; no less lavish of his Gold than of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55190:25"/>Bloud. The Grand <hi>Visier,</hi> and the Cham of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copite Tartary,</hi> were his <hi>Pensioners,</hi> dazl'd with several Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his <hi>Louisian</hi> Medalls; the one to divert the Arms of <hi>Poland;</hi> the other to keep his <hi>Imperial Majesty</hi> employ'd in the utmost Limits of his Dominions, bordering upon <hi>Turky,</hi> that he with the less resistence might revel in the Ruins of the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing <hi>Gardens</hi> and <hi>Cities</hi> of the <hi>Rhine.</hi> And as he tramples under foot all <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> at Home, so by tampering with the Ministers and Subjects of other Princes, he instructs them here to manage their fidelity to the best advantage of his own Ambition, and by a <hi>Metal</hi> of his own, tries what <hi>Metal</hi> they are made of before he deal with their Masters. And with this sort of <hi>White Powder,</hi> which does execution without Noise, shoots down more Citadels, Castles, and strong Holds, and takes in more Towns than all the <hi>Thunder</hi> of his <hi>Cannon.</hi> In so much, that it has been observ'd, that when his Ambassadors go abroad, they either carry along with them the Principal <hi>Engins,</hi> or else they are sent after them; an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassador, or an Agent go before his Army and then usually a Conquest follows. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is his <hi>Motto:</hi> A new way to Honour and Renown, unknown to <hi>Alexander,</hi> or any of the dull <hi>Roman</hi> Conquerors.</p>
            <p>Had not the Steward of Commissary General <hi>Capellier</hi>'s House been tainted with this golden <hi>Poison,</hi> he had never been surpriz'd by his Master in the very Act of <hi>Traiterous Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondence</hi> with the Minister of <hi>France,</hi> to whom he gave an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act accompt of all he could discover in his Master's House. And to confirm what his Master had detected, at length cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Letters, which the Steward was to have received from the <hi>French</hi> Minister, were seiz'd at the Imperial <hi>Post-Office</hi> in <hi>Frankford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> the City of <hi>Strasburgh</hi> thought it self in full security, confirm'd by several <hi>fervent</hi> and <hi>vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> Letters, which the <hi>French</hi> King wrote to them from time to time, and the assurances given them by his Resident abiding in the City, that his Master <hi>desir'd</hi> nothing more than to live in Peace and Amity with the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and with the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55190:26"/>Cities of the Empire. And yet by the <hi>underhand,</hi> conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and tampering with the same <hi>Resident,</hi> a Traitor was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen <hi>Burghermaster,</hi> who acted altogether conformable to the Advice of <hi>France.</hi> On the other side, the <hi>Magistrates</hi> and <hi>Burghesses</hi> being lull'd asleep by the fair Promises and Protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>France,</hi> dismiss'd their Guard of <hi>Switzers,</hi> which were the chief security of their City: But no sooner were the <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers</hi> departed, but <hi>Monsieur Louvoy</hi> with a powerfull Army invested the City, and forc'd them to surrender upon such Conditions as he was pleas'd to prescribe them. After which the <hi>French</hi> King made no scruple to violate those pitifull <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> which they granted them, and to treat them as <hi>Slaves</hi> like the rest of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>The Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen</hi> began in the Name of the most holy and indivisible Trinity; and the end of it was, that there should be an immoveable and unshaken Peace between his <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Majesty</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King, to stop the <hi>desolation</hi> of so many Provinces, and the Effusion of so much <hi>Christian Bloud;</hi> yet, no sooner was the Emperor engag'd against the <hi>Turk,</hi> and that <hi>Spain</hi> and her Allies had laid down their Arms and disbanded the greatest part of their Forces, relying upon the <hi>Faith</hi> of the Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> but the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King fell in upon <hi>Flanders</hi> with a more than <hi>Turkish</hi> Fury, <hi>Burning, Plundring,</hi> and <hi>Levelling</hi> with the Earth whole <hi>Towns</hi> and <hi>Villages,</hi> on purpose to constrain the People to revolt, and to become his Vassals to preserve themselves from utter ruin.</p>
            <p>The Correspondence of the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King with the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Port, is too well known, and how it was at his Most <hi>Christian</hi> Importunity, that the Grand Seignior broke the first Truce which he had made with the Empire, to second the designs of Count <hi>Teckeley,</hi> whom <hi>France,</hi> out of a particular Zeal to the <hi>Catholick Religion,</hi> assisted with Men and Money, and that prevailing charm it was that wrought upon the Port to send back Count <hi>Caprara,</hi> and reject the Propositions of Peace which he carry'd along with him. Of which the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quess of <hi>Seppeville,</hi> then the <hi>French</hi> Ambassador at <hi>Viena,</hi> fail'd
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:55190:26"/>not with all diligence to give his Master Notice; who with no less sedulity dispatch'd another Person to the Grand Visier, to oblige and encourage him to contrive the Seige of <hi>Vienna,</hi> urging him that it was for his Honour not to quit it; That the City was at its last Gasp, and that it behov'd him to take it, whatever it cost him, for the sake of his Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the publick Good of the Port; for that the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ige having made such a noise in the World, he could not leave the prosecution of it without Eternal Infamy to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, and the Grand <hi>Vizier;</hi> adding withall, that to facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the taking of the Town, and to divide the Emperors Forces, his Master would enter into <hi>Flanders</hi> with a Puissant Army, which would infallibly oblige the Princes of the <hi>Empire,</hi> to recall their Forces for their own Security. And in that point, he was as good as his Word to the <hi>Turk,</hi> entring <hi>Flanders</hi> at the same time with <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Sword,</hi> as if he had been second to <hi>Mahomet.</hi> But when <hi>Vienna</hi> was reliev'd, he was so far from partaking in the general Joy of the rest of the <hi>Christian</hi> World, that he forbid his <hi>Ecclesiasticks</hi> to observe any <hi>Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving</hi> for the <hi>Victory</hi> of the <hi>Christians,</hi> upon pain of incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his High Displeasure.</p>
            <p>Nor is it only by the assistence of open and profess'd <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels,</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> King fights the <hi>Emperor</hi> abroad, but by the means of his pretended <hi>Friends,</hi> and nearest <hi>Counsellors,</hi> who having finger'd the <hi>Gold</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> become <hi>Traitors</hi> to their <hi>Lawfull Prince,</hi> and betray his very <hi>Cabinet Secrets.</hi> This occasion'd the misunderstanding that happen'd between the Duke of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> and <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> General of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Forces in the <hi>Holland</hi> War.</p>
            <p>For in the Year 1672. when all <hi>Europe</hi> look'd upon the <hi>Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces</hi> near the brink of <hi>Destruction,</hi> the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> fore seeing the consequences to be expected from the successfull enterprises of <hi>France,</hi> took the Field with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Army, at what time <hi>Montecuculi</hi> was on his March, with a design to act jointly. Upon which <hi>Turenne</hi> was sent to oppose those two Armies, but by the several <hi>Marches</hi> and <hi>Counter Marches</hi> which the Elector made, <hi>Turenne</hi>'s Army
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55190:27"/>was so tir'd and harrass'd, that about the end of the <hi>Campaigne</hi> it was in so miserable a condition, that all <hi>Turenne</hi> could doe, was to defend himself; which caus'd the <hi>Elector</hi> to make a vigorus Remonstrance of all things to be made to the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Council.</hi> Which wrought so effectually, that positive Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were sent <hi>Montecuculi</hi> to join the Elector and fight <hi>Turenne,</hi> without farther loss of time; so that nothing but <hi>Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> the mode of <hi>France,</hi> could have prevented the Total Ruine of <hi>Turenne</hi>'s Army. But the <hi>French</hi> Instruments in the <hi>Imperial Court</hi> so order'd the matter, that <hi>Montecuculi</hi>'s Orders were chang'd, and an express command sent him, neither to joyn the Elector, nor to fight <hi>Turenne.</hi> The Elector, who had receiv'd from the Court of <hi>Vienna</hi> a formal Letter, which gave him an Account of the true Order which the Emperor had sent his <hi>General</hi> to joyn him, and fight the shatter'd Enemies, wonder'd when <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> being by him summond to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Order, refus'd to obey it: But <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> who knew nothing of the Letter sent the Elector, could do no less than follow his own Instructions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Elector</hi> was concern'd in <hi>Reputation</hi> to make the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> sensible of <hi>Montecuculi</hi>'s proceedings; and if <hi>Montecuculi</hi> was strangely surpriz'd, when at his return to <hi>Vienna,</hi> his <hi>Imperial Majesty</hi> call'd him to a strict Account, why he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther join'd the <hi>Brandenburgher,</hi> nor fought <hi>Turenne,</hi> the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> was no less amaz'd, when his General produced for his discharge an <hi>Order</hi> in exact form, forbidding him to doe either the one or the other. This was a perfect Mystery, however, afterwards it was found out to have been a contrivance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>French Emissaries,</hi> and some of the <hi>Imperial Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,</hi> who having easily found a way to intercept the <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Order,</hi> and in the same Dispatch to transmit a false one under a counterfeited Hand and Seal. And thus perhaps it was that <hi>General Souches,</hi> after the Battle of <hi>Senneff,</hi> drew off from the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and left him in the Lurch, under pretence of not having order to doe any more than what he had done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tarbrack</hi> was a Town upon the Borders of <hi>Germany,</hi> that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55190:27"/>stood conveniently for the purposes of the <hi>French</hi> King, and therefore he resolv'd to fortifie it. On the other side, the <hi>Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alists</hi> complain'd of it to the <hi>French</hi> King, as a Truce and Treaty both at one time; but all the Answer they could get, was, that the <hi>Royal Chamber</hi> of <hi>Mets</hi> had irrevocably decreed it to belong to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Imperialists</hi> had no reason to complain of a Sovereign <hi>Monarch</hi>'s fortifying his Frontier Towns.</p>
            <p>His very proposals of <hi>Marriage</hi> are only <hi>snares</hi> to entrap such Princes as will accept of his <hi>Matches;</hi> and because his main design is at the Empire, therefore he strives to scatter his <hi>Crrces</hi> and <hi>Medias</hi> among the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> Believing Wives to be the fittest Instruments to betray their Husbands, and the nuptial sheets to be the seeurest <hi>Harbours</hi> for <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus after the Marquess of <hi>Bethune</hi>'s Sister was married to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> jealousies between the <hi>King</hi> her <hi>Husband</hi> and the <hi>Emperor</hi> were fomented, and Factions set up in that Country, by the means of those <hi>Golden Rays</hi> which the Sun of <hi>France</hi> displays in that Court by the Hands of the <hi>Bankers</hi> of <hi>Hamburgh</hi> and <hi>Dantzick.</hi> And the more to encourage her to play her Gaime according to the <hi>French Instructions,</hi> his Most <hi>Christian</hi> Majesty made her Father a <hi>Duke</hi> and <hi>Peer</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and promis'd to receive her as a <hi>Queen,</hi> and not as a <hi>Subject,</hi> if she return'd a <hi>Widow,</hi> in her own <hi>Country.</hi> Thus he thought to have caught the Young Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> with one of his natural <hi>Daughters;</hi> but that <hi>Heroick Prince</hi> despis'd the Motion. And if the <hi>French</hi> King were assur'd that the Young Prince of <hi>Poland</hi> should succeed his Father, there is another natural <hi>Daughter</hi> of <hi>France</hi> ready prepar'd for him; for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, it would be a <hi>Daughter</hi> merely thrown away, if she could not be in a Station to serve her own <hi>Country.</hi> For that the main end of the <hi>French</hi> King, in giving <hi>French</hi> Wives to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the several Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> is to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the strength of the <hi>Empire,</hi> and lessen the Authority of the <hi>Emperor,</hi> by separating from his interest the particular Princes of the Empire by private <hi>Intrigues,</hi> and distinct
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55190:28"/>
               <hi>Treaties,</hi> which though it be contrary to the Treaty of <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> yet that signifies nothing to a Prince who has no such <hi>Veneration</hi> for <hi>Leagues</hi> as to think them worth observing.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>French</hi> King's dealing with the Duke of <hi>Nieuburgh</hi> it was somewhat <hi>Barbarous;</hi> for that, after the <hi>French</hi> King had caus'd him to <hi>Mortgage</hi> the greatest part of his <hi>Estate</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most beyond the hopes of <hi>Redemption,</hi> in expectation of the <hi>Polish Crown,</hi> to which <hi>France</hi> had promis'd to advance him by the assistence of a <hi>strong Party,</hi> which she had in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, contrary to the <hi>Treaties,</hi> as well with the <hi>Duke</hi> as with the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and to his reiterated <hi>Promises</hi> and <hi>Vows,</hi> both by word of <hi>Mouth</hi> and in <hi>Writing;</hi> he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, by his <hi>Creatures</hi> and <hi>Agents,</hi> oppos'd the <hi>Duke</hi>'s preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, and endeavoured with all the industry and importunity imaginable, to have the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> preferr'd before him, and all the rest of his Competitors; a sufficient warning to all Princes how they relie upon the <hi>broken Reed</hi> of <hi>French</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity.</p>
            <p>The Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> was environed with <hi>French Emissaries</hi> and <hi>Spies,</hi> and some of his Principal <hi>Ministers</hi> so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicated with the Elixirs of <hi>France,</hi> that nothing was said or done in his <hi>Palace,</hi> of which the <hi>French</hi> Envoy had not swift <hi>Intelligence.</hi> And the World was well inform'd of all the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues</hi> and large <hi>Presents,</hi> which Monsieur <hi>De Rebenack</hi> scatter'd about in that Court; of which the <hi>Agent</hi> himself was so unwary, or so foolish, as to make his boasts.</p>
            <p>The Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> better understood his own Interest, and therefore would not bite at the <hi>Golden Hook,</hi> as one that disdain'd the treacherous <hi>Offers</hi> of <hi>France;</hi> but the <hi>French</hi> King endeavour'd by other ways to raise him disturbances in his own <hi>Family,</hi> and to set him at Variance with his <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> which would have strangely imbroild him, had not the Emperor in time provided against those <hi>Mischiefs.</hi> However, lest it should be said there was any <hi>Court</hi> in <hi>Christendom,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>French</hi> King had not some <hi>Plough</hi> or other going, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bears not to send into <hi>Saxony</hi> such as know how to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate themselves to the <hi>Humour</hi> of the <hi>Country,</hi> more espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55190:28"/>the stoutest <hi>Drinkers</hi> he can find out, who by that means, making themselves familiar at the <hi>Tables</hi> of the <hi>Great Persons,</hi> watch their opportunities in the highth of <hi>Jollity</hi> and <hi>Compotation</hi> to draw the <hi>Worms</hi> out of their <hi>Noses,</hi> and dive into the bottoms of their open'd hearts.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Palatine</hi> Electors, neither Father nor Son, would close with the Interest of the <hi>French,</hi> and therefore his most <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian</hi> Majesty sacrificed the depopulated Cities of that Country to his <hi>Fury,</hi> even to the compassion of some that were the Executioners of his <hi>Rage;</hi> a Depopulation which none but such Monsters of Men as the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King employs would have undertaken; Men so impious and fearless of God, that one of them being mildly reprehended for the <hi>burning</hi> of a fair <hi>Town,</hi> reply'd, <hi>That he would burn God in Heaven, if his Master the King of</hi> France <hi>commanded him to doe it.</hi> But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King is of the Opinion of the <hi>Antient Galls,</hi> believing there is no way to give peace to a Country, but by rooting out the Inhabitants, according to that of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus, Galli, ubi solitudinem fecerunt, pacem appellant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor could the Bishop of <hi>Munster,</hi> as cunning as he was, preserve himself from being out-witted by the <hi>French</hi> infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For that being comprehended in the League of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> when he found himself attack'd by the States of <hi>Holland</hi> within the Empire, he implored the Aid of <hi>France</hi> according to the <hi>Guarranty,</hi> but in vain; for which when he was about to make his complaint, he was of a sudden overwhelm'd with the Forces of <hi>France,</hi> and had not his Enemies us'd Moderation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him more than his own <hi>Allie,</hi> his Territories though the <hi>Patrimony</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> had been laid in Ashes before now.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>French</hi> King broke Faith with <hi>Holland,</hi> to the surprize of a great part of their <hi>Country,</hi> he was so far from assigning any <hi>Cause, true</hi> or <hi>false,</hi> for his Actions, that he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publish'd a <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>War</hi> without any other <hi>Reasons,</hi> than only the <hi>Ill satisfaction which His Majesty had of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of the States General toward him, being risen to that Degree, that he can no longer without Diminution of his Glory, dissemble his Indignation against them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore he had
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:55190:29"/>resolv'd to make War against them by Sea and Land,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And commands all his Subjects</hi> courit sus <hi>upon the</hi> Hollanders, <hi>for such is Our Pleasure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly it was never known that in any Age or Nation in the World the Sword was drawn upon no better Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; a style so far from being Most <hi>Christian,</hi> that nothing but some <hi>French Romance</hi> could parallel the Expression. All that can be said, 'twas <hi>A la-mode de France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Holland</hi> had no reason to wonder at these proceedings, considering what a <hi>Prank</hi> the <hi>French.</hi> King had plaid them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when he pretended to joyn with them in the War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>England.</hi> At what time <hi>France,</hi> by virtue of a Treaty of <hi>Guarranty</hi> with the States of the United Provinces, after se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral requests ineffectually made by the States, found her self oblig'd to make a shew of undertaking to defend them against <hi>England;</hi> among the rest of the <hi>Articles,</hi> there was one by which it was concluded and agreed in express terms, that the <hi>Allies</hi> should not <hi>Negotiate,</hi> much less conclude any Peace or Truce with the common Enemy, without the consent of the other, and without procuring the same satisfaction for his <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi> as he would for himself. The States tied themselves with that <hi>Integrity</hi> to this Obligation, that notwithstanding the considerable Advantages offer'd them to treat separately; they would not so much as lend an Ear to any Proposition of that <hi>Nature. France</hi> on the other side, had always kept on <hi>Foot</hi> a private <hi>Negotiation,</hi> which nevertheless the <hi>Dutch</hi> had all the <hi>Reason</hi> in the <hi>World</hi> to suspect, because of the continual Post<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Curriers</hi> between <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>London.</hi> However <hi>France</hi> confirm'd them so authentickly in a contrary belief, and gave them such positive Promises, that she would never hearken to any Proposition, unless in a joint Assembly, for a <hi>General Peace,</hi> that she order'd the Count <hi>D' Estrades,</hi> that in Case the <hi>States</hi> would not give <hi>Credit</hi> to what he assured them as an <hi>Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour,</hi> he should quit that <hi>Character</hi> for so long time, and pawn his Faith to them as a Private Person. A great honour indeed to the <hi>Count d' Estrade,</hi> to have the Reputation of a Person that would not tell an untruth, but under the <hi>Character</hi> of a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55190:29"/>Publick <hi>Minister</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and that the <hi>Probity</hi> of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son was above the <hi>Dignity</hi> of his <hi>Employment.</hi> Though had he been so improvident to have been bound for his Master, he must certainly have answered both the <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Interest;</hi> for certain it is that <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> concluded the Peace without the <hi>consent</hi> or so much as the <hi>knowledge</hi> of the <hi>States;</hi> neither did <hi>France</hi> make any mention of them or their Interests, or of any reserve or relation to the <hi>General Peace.</hi> But that which was more <hi>surprizing</hi> was this, that after the <hi>French</hi> King had thus concluded a <hi>private Peace</hi> with <hi>England,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing he had promis'd the King not to exercise any <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Hostility</hi> against him, he us'd all his endeavours to oblige the <hi>Dutch</hi> to put forth their <hi>Fleet</hi> to <hi>Sea, engaging</hi> to join with them, and <hi>agreeing</hi> upon all the <hi>Conditions</hi> necessary for that purpose. A double headed peice of <hi>Treachery,</hi> fit to be recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the <hi>Eternal Infamy</hi> of the <hi>Faith Breaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we look into <hi>Sweden,</hi> we shall find that she was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider'd as more potent than <hi>Denmark,</hi> and therefore a <hi>League</hi> was clapt up with them, to prevent the <hi>Danes</hi> assisting <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and by that <hi>League</hi> the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was to receive by way of <hi>Pension</hi> or <hi>Gratuity,</hi> Sixteen Hundred Thousand <hi>Crowns.</hi> But the <hi>French,</hi> upon second <hi>Thoughts,</hi> finding the <hi>Treaty</hi> with the <hi>Sweeds</hi> to be of little use to them, refus'd to ratifie it, and sent away <hi>Monsieur Trelon,</hi> to tell the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> in short, that his Master declard it void; a quick and <hi>Majestick</hi> way to rescind a <hi>Treaty</hi> at any time.</p>
            <p>If we remove into <hi>Poland,</hi> there you shall find no body more <hi>busie</hi> than the <hi>French</hi> King's <hi>Ambassadors</hi> at the <hi>Elections</hi> of the King, to procure the choice of such a one as may be tack'd to his <hi>Interest,</hi> or at least such a one as may have no kindness to the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>Austria,</hi> and all this to enable him the more to disturb the Peace of the <hi>Empire.</hi> In pursuance of which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly designs, under a pretence of Advancing the <hi>Affairs</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> and settling a perfect <hi>Amity</hi> with that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King contriv'd a <hi>Marriage</hi> for the <hi>Polish Prince,</hi> with a <hi>Lady</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> By which means he had a fair opportunity to send thither as her <hi>Attendents,</hi> and for the more <hi>Splendor</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:55190:30"/>of her <hi>Fame,</hi> so many expert <hi>Instruments</hi> of <hi>Mischief,</hi> that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately they form'd and settl'd a <hi>Cabal</hi> with such <hi>Intrigues</hi> as in a short time <hi>enflam'd</hi> the <hi>Nobility</hi> of that <hi>Kingdom</hi> into <hi>Animosities</hi> and <hi>Factions,</hi> not likely to be so soon again <hi>extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish'd:</hi> And at that time they wrought so far, that the King soon after became willing to resign the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> upon which, the <hi>Turk,</hi> seeing the great <hi>Divisions</hi> that were rais'd among them, was the more easily allur'd in by the <hi>French Cabal,</hi> who procur'd by <hi>Versallian</hi>'s directions that <hi>Mischief,</hi> partly out of <hi>revenge</hi> because they could not compass another King either of <hi>French Bloud</hi> or <hi>French Interest</hi> at the next <hi>Election,</hi> and partly, because the <hi>New King</hi> had contracted a <hi>Marriage</hi> with the <hi>Emperour</hi>'s Sister.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Poland,</hi> by reason of its <hi>Situation,</hi> being shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered under the <hi>Wings</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Ambassador, is fix'd upon by the <hi>French,</hi> to convey themselves from thence into <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> and the <hi>Ottoman Port,</hi> for the better and more easie carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on their <hi>Intrigues</hi> between <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Male Contents,</hi> and the <hi>Turk.</hi> And first, it appear'd by several <hi>Letters</hi> dispersed both in <hi>Constantinople, Transilvania,</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> that upon the 30th. of <hi>December,</hi> 1681. the War was resolv'd upon, and Sworn to against the Emperor, in the <hi>Serraglio</hi> of <hi>Constantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> in the <hi>Holy Council,</hi> call'd the <hi>Divan,</hi> where the <hi>Mufti, High Priest</hi> of the <hi>Mahomitan</hi> Religion, sits President. Which sufficiently laid open the Authors and Procurers of that War, and clearly shew'd, that the <hi>French</hi> were not asham'd, as if it had been a famous <hi>Action</hi> in them to take advice of the <hi>Divan,</hi> and applaud the success of the <hi>Negotiation,</hi> as they did in their <hi>Letters</hi> written backwards and forwards to the <hi>Rebels,</hi> in which they congratulated with the <hi>Rebels;</hi> for having drawn the <hi>Rebels</hi> to their Succour, they promis'd each other in their <hi>Letters</hi> all the <hi>Advantages</hi> they could expect, which aim'd at no less than to have driven the Emperor out of the best of his <hi>Dominions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was known that such of the <hi>Hungarians</hi> as were forc'd to run their <hi>Country</hi> for conspiring against the Emperor, liv'd on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon such supplies of Money as they receiv'd from the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55190:30"/>
               <hi>French,</hi> to the end they should not be constrain'd to make their <hi>Peace</hi> with the <hi>Emperour,</hi> whose <hi>Clemency</hi> they were made believe extended no farther than to offer it; so that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd to prosecute their Enterprize upon the Promises that were made them from <hi>France.</hi> Which was the reason that <hi>Akakia</hi> renewed and confirm'd more powerfully than ever the <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Alliance</hi> with the <hi>Male-Contents</hi> in <hi>Hungary.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> Emissaries also, without any shame of violating the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> and in <hi>Countries</hi> where the Solemn <hi>Treaty</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> was in full force, though they had been manifestly disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in a secret <hi>Conspiracy,</hi> run on afterwards more than ever with an unparallell'd <hi>Impudence,</hi> as if all things had been law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them to act without controul.</p>
            <p>An Hunderd Thousand <hi>Florins</hi> were ordered at <hi>Paris</hi> to so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the <hi>Discontents</hi> of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Rebels, and quicken the Motion of the <hi>Turks;</hi> which summ was deliver'd at <hi>Dant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zick,</hi> and paid into the Hands of a <hi>Banker,</hi> who afterwards deliver'd it into the Hands of the <hi>French Emissaries,</hi> at several Payments, the better to hide the Business. And the <hi>Sieur du Vernay Boucauldi, Count Teckely</hi>'s real Spie, caus'd to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd to the <hi>Sieur Valentine Nemessan</hi> 11300 <hi>Duckats,</hi> to oblige the <hi>Male-Contents</hi> to take <hi>Arms</hi> again, and attack the Citta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of <hi>Zatmar,</hi> after the <hi>French</hi> Mode; that is, to endeavour to gain the <hi>Garrison</hi> or <hi>Citizens</hi> with Money.</p>
            <p>These <hi>Tricks</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Emissaries were so well known, that the Princess <hi>Radzivilliana</hi> forbad the suffering any <hi>French</hi> to pass through her Countrey of <hi>Saculia,</hi> fearing lest they should as in other Places, corrupt her People with Money, and one being taken passing through her <hi>Countrey,</hi> was by her command laden with <hi>Irons,</hi> and severely <hi>punish'd.</hi> Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less they took other <hi>Roads,</hi> and had frequent private enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>views with <hi>Valentin Nemessan, Peter Jagel,</hi> and other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Friends and Allies of <hi>Teckely.</hi> They made it their Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness likewise to have more and more frequent conferences in <hi>Transilvania,</hi> sending first one, and then another to <hi>Paris</hi> with ample Accounts of their Proceedings, and for farther In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:55190:31"/>
            <p>Of all these things the Emperours Ambassador in the Court of <hi>Poland</hi> complain'd to his Majesty, and desir'd that no <hi>French</hi> Man, not being an Ambassador, or bearing some other Employment, might be permitted to stay in his <hi>Dominions.</hi> Upon which the King gave Notice to the <hi>French</hi> Ambassador, to order <hi>Akakia</hi> and <hi>Du Vernay</hi> to withdraw: The <hi>Senate</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so told the same Ambassador, that they well understood that the <hi>French</hi> were they who had stirr'd up the <hi>Troubles</hi> in <hi>Hungary;</hi> that they knew what <hi>Money</hi> had been given for it, what <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals</hi> they had held, and what the <hi>Sieur du Vernay</hi> kept every day. They declared him to be a <hi>Spie,</hi> and that he had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther business to detain him about <hi>Leopold,</hi> but only to treat with the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Mahometans</hi> about drawing the <hi>War</hi> into <hi>Hungary.</hi> The Ambassador answered, that <hi>Vernay</hi> was sent with him into <hi>Poland</hi> to manage the <hi>Affairs</hi> of the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King his <hi>Master,</hi> and deny'd that either <hi>Vernay</hi> or he had any commerce with the <hi>Hungarians</hi> or <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Spanish</hi> Ambassador having made new <hi>Discoveries,</hi> renew'd his complaints to the King, who gave him <hi>Audience</hi> in the presence of <hi>Vitry</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Ambassador, and before the whole <hi>Senate;</hi> where he spoke a long time against the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable <hi>Methods</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of the <hi>French,</hi> carry'd on by <hi>Vernay,</hi> to promote the <hi>Troubles</hi> of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and bring the <hi>Turks</hi> into <hi>Christendem;</hi> but then it was that <hi>Vitry,</hi> having no way to avoid it, declar'd <hi>Vernay</hi> to be joint Ambassador with him from the <hi>French</hi> King; by that means to shelter a <hi>Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> to <hi>Christendom</hi> under the Protection of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much about the same time the <hi>Castellan</hi> of <hi>Primistau</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that neither His Majesty of <hi>Poland</hi> nor the <hi>Senate</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd the <hi>French</hi> Spies, and moreover that their designs still succeeded better and better, refus'd to permit <hi>Vernay</hi> to enter his <hi>Village</hi> of <hi>Nimoravia,</hi> but sorced him to pass another way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vitry</hi> was highly incens'd at this, and going directly to Court, laid before the King the <hi>Affront</hi> and <hi>Indignity</hi> offer'd to his Associate <hi>Vernay,</hi> and was so bold as to demand the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment</hi> of the <hi>Castellan</hi> for satisfaction; but the King not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55190:31"/>enduring his <hi>Confidence,</hi> told him plainly, that it was to no purpose to couch <hi>Vernay</hi> under the Quality of an Ambassador, for that the <hi>Tragedies</hi> he acted under the vain pretence of an Ambassador, were too well known; that all the <hi>devices</hi> of the <hi>French,</hi> and their <hi>contracts</hi> with the <hi>Turk</hi> were discover'd, that the places which <hi>Vernay</hi> had corrupted were named; their <hi>Resolutions</hi> and <hi>Designs</hi> known, that he could exactly tell how much Money had been remitted from <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Hungary,</hi> and how they had us'd <hi>Violence, Deceit,</hi> and wicked <hi>Practice</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Emperour, to the misfortune of <hi>Christendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ambassador would have pretended to have clear'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self of these things, which he said were <hi>wrongfully</hi> charg'd upon his Nation. But the King growing <hi>hot,</hi> would not hear him, only told the Ambassador he would lay Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand <hi>Pistoles</hi> with him, that he would <hi>undeniably</hi> prove all that he had said to be true.</p>
            <p>At which the <hi>French</hi> Ambassador stood amaz'd, and by his silence sufficiently <hi>confirm'd</hi> the thing. The rest of the <hi>French</hi> that were present also, in a <hi>Consternation</hi> fix'd their <hi>Eyes</hi> upon the <hi>Ground;</hi> not lifting them up, but to gaze upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as it were <hi>accusing</hi> themselves. So certain it is, that the inward reproach of <hi>Conscience,</hi> and the secret <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> put the most fierce and confident out of <hi>Countenance,</hi> and by reducing the <hi>Guilty</hi> to a shamefull <hi>Silence,</hi> force them to make some sort of confession of their <hi>Crimes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Besides what has been recited, there were several <hi>Letters</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted, which clear'd up the <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Hungarian</hi> Male-Contents. One from Monsieur <hi>Vernay</hi> to <hi>Count Teckely,</hi> wherein the <hi>French</hi> Spie tells him, that he had receiv'd with great joy the <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> which he sent him from the <hi>Camp</hi> before <hi>Filleck,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clos'd in the Packets of the <hi>French</hi> Ambassador at <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</hi> That he had endeavour'd to send <hi>Jaygell</hi> what he had promis'd him, and what he had receiv'd, but wanted an Opportunity; farther he desir'd the <hi>Count</hi> to order it so, that his <hi>Messengers</hi> should come to him by <hi>Night,</hi> and directed him which Road they should take, to avoid the Searches of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:55190:32"/>the <hi>Polonians,</hi> concluding that he should take care in all things that the Count should be pleas'd to command him.</p>
            <p>Another <hi>Letter</hi> from Count <hi>Teckely</hi> to <hi>Vernay,</hi> wherein the Count gives <hi>Vernay</hi> thanks to his faithfull Agent <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Nemessani,</hi> and promises him to acknowledge it, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion should serve; gives him an account of his taking <hi>Cas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sovia</hi> and <hi>Filleck,</hi> and how he intended to prosecute his good Success.</p>
            <p>Another <hi>Letter</hi> from <hi>Peter Jaygell</hi> Governour of <hi>Cassovia</hi> to Monsieur <hi>Vernay;</hi> wherein <hi>Jaygell</hi> gives <hi>Vernay</hi> an Account of the taking and dismantling of <hi>Filleck,</hi> that <hi>Teckely</hi> had been Proclaim'd King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and confirm'd in that Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity by the Great <hi>Turk,</hi> who sent him from the Port a <hi>Hat</hi> instead of a <hi>Crown,</hi> a <hi>Standard,</hi> and a <hi>Sceptre.</hi> He tells <hi>Vernay</hi> farther, that <hi>Nemessani</hi> was gone to treat of <hi>Affairs</hi> at the <hi>French</hi> King's Court, and presses <hi>Vernay</hi> to hasten the supply promis'd by the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>Sufficient Proofs of the pernicious and Most <hi>Anti-Christian</hi> Treacheries of the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King to the ruin of <hi>Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> After all this, to shew the extent of <hi>French</hi> falshood, you shall see that if it stand with his own Interest, the <hi>French</hi> King will not stick to betray himself, and discover his own <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons;</hi> for that at the beginning of the <hi>Dutch</hi> War, when he saw the Emperour arming himself in good earnest to assist the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to dissuade and divert him from his purpose; and to engage him, had it been possible, not to concern himself in the <hi>Quarrel,</hi> he very fairly offer'd to deliver into the Emperour's hands all the Original <hi>Letters</hi> and <hi>Papers</hi> he had receiv'd from time to time from his <hi>brib'd Friends</hi> and Creatures in <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> to the end that both his <hi>Imperial Majesty</hi> and the King of <hi>Poland</hi> might take such Orders as they thought fit with those <hi>Traitors,</hi> which may serve as a fare warning and determent to all those that prefer <hi>French</hi> Money before their Loyalty, and the true Interests of their Country.</p>
            <p>'Tis true that for some time the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King made the raising of his Seige from before <hi>Luxenburgh</hi> a great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of his <hi>Christian</hi> Zeal and Generosity to his Imperial
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:55190:32"/>Majesty, not to assail him when the <hi>Turk</hi> was at his Doors, but the true ground of his retiring, was this notwithstanding his specious pretences, at the instance of the Confederates, all good Offices were done by the King of <hi>England,</hi> and Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials given, but all to no effect, till the word <hi>Parliament</hi> was put into them. That powerfull word had such a <hi>charm</hi> in it, that even at a distance it raised the <hi>Siege;</hi> which may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us of what <hi>Efficacy</hi> a King of <hi>England</hi>'s words are when he will give them their full weight, and threaten with his <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then it is that he appears that greater <hi>Figure</hi> which we ought to represent him in our <hi>Minds,</hi> the Nation his <hi>Body,</hi> he the <hi>Head,</hi> and join'd with that <hi>Harmony</hi> that every word he pronounces is the Word of a <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Such Words are as effectual as <hi>Fleets</hi> and <hi>Armies,</hi> because they can create them; and without this, his Word sounds abroad like a <hi>Faint Whis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> that is either not heard, or which is worse, not min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>But to return to the <hi>French</hi> King, and bring him home to his own <hi>Dominions,</hi> where you shall find his extraordinary <hi>Kindness</hi> to his then Highness the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> in <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molishing</hi> the <hi>Castle,</hi> and pulling down the <hi>Walls</hi> of the chief <hi>City</hi> of his <hi>Principality</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> to save him the expence of a <hi>Garrison,</hi> and <hi>Plundering</hi> and <hi>Exacting</hi> vast Summs of Money from the <hi>Subjects</hi> of another <hi>Prince,</hi> living in Peace and giving him no Disturbance, merely under pretence of entertaining the Children of <hi>Hugonots.</hi> Nay, you shall find him persecuting his own <hi>Subjects</hi> under the Name of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> and sending his Missionary <hi>Dragoons</hi> to convert them by ransacking their <hi>Houses,</hi> robbing them of their <hi>Goods,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing their <hi>Wives,</hi> deflowring their <hi>Daughters,</hi> and inflicting upon the <hi>Men</hi> torments more <hi>cruel</hi> and <hi>inhumane</hi> than those of the <hi>Ten Persecutions;</hi> and all this while, they were under the <hi>Protection</hi> of several Edicts, solemnly granted and ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them for the Exercise of their Religion without distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:55190:33"/>
            <p>These are the Renowned Acts of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. displaying the lovely prospect of his <hi>Falshood</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> his breach of <hi>Faith</hi> with <hi>Spain,</hi> his <hi>Infidelity</hi> to <hi>Holland,</hi> his <hi>Juggling</hi> with the <hi>Northern</hi> Princes, his <hi>Treacherous Aspiring</hi> to the <hi>Imperial Throne,</hi> his vast <hi>Expences</hi> to divide the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> from the <hi>Empire,</hi> his <hi>endangering</hi> the <hi>subversion</hi> of all <hi>Christendom</hi> by confederating with the <hi>Turk,</hi> and his <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olations</hi> of the <hi>Peace</hi> of his own <hi>Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, it has been his common <hi>Practice</hi> to give the World all manner of <hi>Disturbance,</hi> and to render <hi>France</hi> the common <hi>Enemy</hi> of the <hi>Peace</hi> of Mankind; and a publick <hi>Pest</hi> among all States and Princes; in every Countrey and Kingdom he either finds <hi>Combustible Stuff,</hi> or else makes it, and then sets <hi>Fire</hi> to it, being at an excessive charge to find <hi>Fod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> for the various Animals of <hi>Faction</hi> in all <hi>Places.</hi> Which sort of <hi>Politicks</hi> appear to be so much the more <hi>Criminal,</hi> because there is no just revenging them, but that which obliges all generous <hi>Nations</hi> to fight their <hi>Enemies</hi> with their <hi>Arms</hi> in their hands, and openly. There being nothing so base as that which makes Men make use of wicked <hi>devices</hi> and execrable <hi>Treasons</hi> as the instruments to ruine others; nor does he that thinks to assume the Name of <hi>Great</hi> by unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Artifices, render himself a whit the more truly <hi>Glorious:</hi> Souls truly Royal and Magnanimous have always despis'd the Conquests they could more easily obtain by <hi>Cunning</hi> and <hi>Trapan,</hi> than by <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Arms:</hi> And it was out of their Opinion, worthy a Noble Spirit, that <hi>Alexander</hi> the great sharply rebuk'd his Favourite <hi>Parmenio,</hi> who would have put him upon a crafty contrivance, telling him, it was only fit for <hi>Robbers</hi> to have recourse to <hi>Treachery,</hi> as their only meanes to compass their <hi>Theiveries.</hi> But the <hi>French</hi> King is of another <hi>Temper,</hi> and thinks it more safe to conquer by <hi>Divide &amp; Impera,</hi> than by dint of <hi>Sword.</hi> He knows him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self good at <hi>Burning,</hi> witness <hi>Alsatia</hi> and the <hi>Palatinate</hi> laid in <hi>Ashes,</hi> and therefore thinks it better to set other <hi>Countries,</hi> which he cannot otherwise come at, in a Flame by <hi>Treachery</hi> and <hi>Faction,</hi> that having enough to doe to quench their own
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:55190:33"/>Fires at home, they may have neither <hi>Leisure</hi> nor <hi>Power</hi> to hinder his <hi>Projects</hi> abroad.</p>
            <p>Doubtless then, since <hi>England</hi> has so lately seen her <hi>Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Houses</hi> in so sad a conflagration, it is a sufficient Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for her to look to her own, and to secure her self and all <hi>Europe</hi> from such <hi>Boutefeus,</hi> and the said effects of their impious designs.</p>
            <p>Seeing then there is so little credit to be given to the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginian</hi> Faith of <hi>France,</hi> and that all the <hi>Motions</hi> of that aspiring <hi>Monarch</hi> tend directly to the subversion of the whole frame of the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> and to erect a <hi>French Tyranny</hi> over all the enthrall'd <hi>Princes</hi> of this same fourth and best inhabited part of the World, there are two <hi>Motives</hi> which ought to excite the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Christendom,</hi> to take the common cause in <hi>hand:</hi> the one is interest of <hi>State,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the strickt obligation of <hi>Justice.</hi> The first is, the general concern of all the <hi>Potentates</hi> of <hi>Europe;</hi> the second, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular interest of the <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Empire.</hi> We shall only take notice of the former, as being the most <hi>Ʋniversal,</hi> and most considerable in the World, and which will lead us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensibly into the second. The grand concern is now to support the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> which is common to all, and to prevent the introducing of <hi>Maxims</hi> into the World which destroy all commerce among Men, and will certainly render humane <hi>Society</hi> no less dangerous and insupportable than that of <hi>Lions</hi> and <hi>Tygers;</hi> to defend the publick Faith of <hi>Treaties,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from the sight of <hi>Christendom</hi> a scandalous example, which, by the fatal <hi>consequences</hi> of it, will surrender the <hi>most feeble</hi> to the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Pleasure</hi> of the strongest and most <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent;</hi> to stop the <hi>Inundation</hi> of a <hi>Rapid Torrent,</hi> against the impetuosity of which neither <hi>Leagues</hi> nor <hi>Marriages,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Oaths</hi> nor <hi>Ties</hi> of <hi>Bloud</hi> and <hi>Parentage,</hi> neither <hi>Amity</hi> nor <hi>Condescentions,</hi> are <hi>Mounds</hi> or <hi>Damms</hi> sufficient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the common <hi>Bulwark</hi> of <hi>Christendom</hi> against a vast <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign,</hi> which has no other ground than the Insatiable thirst of <hi>Conquest,</hi> no other end than despotick <hi>Domination</hi> by dint of <hi>Arms,</hi> and slight of <hi>Intrigue,</hi> nor any <hi>Limits</hi> but such as
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:55190:34"/>
               <hi>Fortune</hi> shall prescribe. In short, <hi>England</hi> is now to decide the <hi>Fate</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> and to pronounce the Sentence of her <hi>Liberty</hi> or <hi>Bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor does there want justification sufficient to pursue so great and glorious an Undertaking to the utmost, when we consider the <hi>Maxims</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> which are easie to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd from the past and present conduct, her insulting <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,</hi> whose design was to have thrown his <hi>Wash-pot</hi> over the <hi>Empire,</hi> and his <hi>Shoe</hi> over all the rest of <hi>Europe.</hi> The first <hi>Mixim</hi> of <hi>France</hi> is, to make War alwaies abroad, and to exercise her <hi>Young Nobility</hi> at the expence of her <hi>Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi> A <hi>Maxim</hi> very <hi>Politick,</hi> and well adjusted for her own <hi>Advantage;</hi> but very incommodious for all the rest of the <hi>World:</hi> For it is certain the <hi>Genius</hi> of that <hi>Nation</hi> cannot long endure the <hi>Calms</hi> of a <hi>Lazy Peace,</hi> so that if you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find employment for them abroad, they will be framing <hi>Commotions</hi> and <hi>Disturbances</hi> at home. The Eldest Sons of all their <hi>Noble Families</hi> carry away the <hi>Estates</hi> without lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any thing to the <hi>Younger,</hi> but an empty <hi>Title</hi> and their <hi>Swords;</hi> so that being little addicted to <hi>Learning,</hi> and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining the life of <hi>Mechanicks,</hi> nothing remains but <hi>War,</hi> or <hi>Thievery,</hi> to rescue them from <hi>Misery;</hi> which is the reason that the <hi>Politicks</hi> of <hi>France</hi> oblige her to be continually picking Quarrels with her <hi>Nighbours,</hi> to evaporate those <hi>Flames,</hi> which otherwise would <hi>prey</hi> upon her own <hi>Bowels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their second <hi>Maxim</hi> is, to <hi>insinuate</hi> themselves into all sorts of <hi>Affairs</hi> on which hand soever it be, and to make themselves <hi>Ʋmpires</hi> in all <hi>business,</hi> either by <hi>Force</hi> or <hi>Subtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> by <hi>Threatnings,</hi> or under pretence of <hi>Friendship,</hi> to wrig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle themselves into <hi>Treaties</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> where they are Parties interested, as they did in that of the Bishop of <hi>Munster,</hi> and afterwards in the <hi>Assembly</hi> at <hi>Breda.</hi> There never was any Quarrel wherein they had not the <hi>cunning</hi> to pretend some <hi>Interest</hi> or <hi>Right;</hi> and never any People shew'd the least inclination to rebell, but they always made them their <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</hi> But experience tells us, that they never took part in any <hi>War</hi> but to enflame it the more, nor ever interpos'd
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:55190:34"/>in any Peace, to Sow the Seeds of new Differences.</p>
            <p>Their third <hi>Maxim</hi> is to make <hi>Interest of State</hi> the only rule of all their Actions, without having any regard to the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Treaties,</hi> or the <hi>Sanctity</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> or any other Ties of <hi>Parentage</hi> or <hi>Friendship,</hi> according to the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Principle of the D. of <hi>Rohan, That Princes commanded the People, and Interest commanded Princes:</hi> So that all that the <hi>Turks</hi> have gain'd upon <hi>Europe</hi> from the time of <hi>Francis</hi> the First till this time, they owe to their Alliances with <hi>France,</hi> and the Diversions she has made in their favour, by giving disturbance to those that enterpriz'd any thing against the common Enemy.</p>
            <p>Their fourth <hi>Maxim</hi> is, to keep, as much as in them lies, all Foreign States employ'd and divided at home, or else engaged in <hi>Foreign War,</hi> (of which <hi>England</hi> in particular has found the sad <hi>Effects,</hi>) and under pretence of assisting some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times one, sometimes another, to seek their own <hi>Advantages</hi> in the <hi>Troubles</hi> of others.</p>
            <p>These are the <hi>Maxims</hi> of Men that make haste to be <hi>Rich</hi> in <hi>Ignoble Conquests;</hi> and the infallible marks of a profound and vast design, that must be stopp'd in time, to stop the spreading of the <hi>Ambitious Grangrene;</hi> for from a <hi>Royal</hi> and powerfull <hi>Professor</hi> of such <hi>Maxims</hi> as these, there is no <hi>Prince</hi> that can be safe in his <hi>Dominions.</hi> Among private Persons it is the most difficult thing to deal with a Man of a large Conscience; how much more a most <hi>Herculean</hi> task it is to cope with a mighty <hi>Potentate</hi> whose Conscience is no less wide than his <hi>Ambition</hi> is <hi>Vast,</hi> who having eleven Millions of Sterling Pounds, torn from the <hi>Bowels</hi> and <hi>Mouths</hi> of his poor and wanting <hi>Subjects,</hi> at command, to maintain his Wars, and bribe his way to Conquest through all the Fences of <hi>Religion, Morality,</hi> and <hi>Common Justice,</hi> values not the tremendous Anger of <hi>Heaven,</hi> nor the Violation of all the Laws of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> nor the preservative Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of Men to attain his ends. It is said of <hi>Tamerlane,</hi> though a <hi>Soythian</hi> and <hi>Barbarian,</hi> that to one who earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly importun'd him in behalf of <hi>Bajazet,</hi> he made this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:55190:35"/>that he did not punish a <hi>King</hi> but an <hi>impious</hi> and <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farious</hi> Man. The same justification have the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> that they fight not against the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King, but an Anti Christian <hi>Ʋsurper,</hi> who <hi>conquers</hi> to <hi>oppress,</hi> and <hi>oppresses</hi> merely to <hi>support</hi> his <hi>Oppression;</hi> and shew the <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur</hi> of his <hi>Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> has more just pretences to his <hi>Dominions,</hi> than perhaps he has himself, at least far more just than what he has to the conquests which he has wrested out of the hands of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> and the <hi>Emperor. England</hi> has the greatest Reason in the World to recover her Antient, and till lately uncontested <hi>Glory,</hi> and assert her long continued <hi>Dominions</hi> of the <hi>Seas,</hi> usurp'd by the Assistence of a purchas'd <hi>Navy,</hi> which if once <hi>destroy'd,</hi> nothing but the same opportunities could again <hi>recover.</hi> It is said that the <hi>Partcullis</hi> was added to the <hi>Royal Badges</hi> of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> to signifie that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> had a just <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Title,</hi> at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to shut up and open the <hi>Sea</hi> when they thought fit; and it may still be prov'd by several substantial Evidences, that the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Title to the Propriety of the <hi>Sea,</hi> is as good and perhaps better than any Title the <hi>French</hi> King has to any part of his <hi>Dominions</hi> by <hi>Land.</hi> And the Letters are still to be seen in the <hi>Paper-Office</hi> at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> if not remov'd, Written by this King's Grandfather with his own hand to King <hi>James,</hi> to ask leave for some few <hi>Vessels</hi> to Fish for <hi>Sowles,</hi> as he should have occasion for his own Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and it ought to be so agen, for it is only fit that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> should guard the Seas, that so well defend and guard Her. Justice it self now loudly calls to <hi>England</hi> to demand satisfaction for the illegal and vexatious Depredations and Practices committed upon her Merchants, even at the time when she was in strictest <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Combination</hi> with her, to the ruine of her Trade, which is the <hi>Apple</hi> of her <hi>Eye,</hi> and the main support of her <hi>Wooden Walls,</hi> her chiefest <hi>Glory,</hi> and, next under <hi>Heaven,</hi> her chiefest <hi>Safeguard</hi> and <hi>Protection.</hi> She ought in <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> to resent the Indiguities and Affronts so lately put upon her, in making her that ought
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:55190:35"/>to be the <hi>Balance</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> the <hi>Derision</hi> of her <hi>Enemies;</hi> and only the Pity of her Friends; such a generous Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity and Resentment as this would wean the <hi>English</hi> Nation from that fond <hi>Dotage</hi> upon <hi>French</hi> Baubles, <hi>French</hi> Fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and <hi>French</hi> Vermin, to the loss of above Sixteen Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thousand Pounds Yearly to this Kingdom, (there ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been Yearly so much more imported of <hi>French</hi> Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, than exported of ours,) which only serves to enrich the <hi>Capital Foe</hi> to our own <hi>Ruine,</hi> and to fit us for the <hi>Toke</hi> of <hi>French</hi> Slavery. For this is a certain Rule, that the first step to the subducing of a <hi>Nation</hi> is to insinuate into them a good liking, or rather a <hi>dotage</hi> of those that are to be their subduers; and therefore it was, that the <hi>French</hi> King obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, that while the <hi>English</hi> were under the <hi>Conjunction</hi> of, the <hi>Triple League,</hi> there was a general humour in the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in opposition to <hi>France,</hi> insomuch that they had thrown off the <hi>French Mode</hi> and put on <hi>Vests,</hi> to the end we might look the more like a distinct People, and not be under the servility of <hi>Imitation,</hi> which alwaies pays a greater reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>Original,</hi> than is consistent with that Equality which all independent <hi>Nations</hi> should pretend to; I say the the <hi>French</hi> King observing this, did not like this small be ginning of ill <hi>Humours,</hi> wisely considering it as a natural <hi>Introduction,</hi> first to make the World his <hi>Apes,</hi> and then his <hi>Slaves;</hi> and therefore he set his Instruments at work to <hi>Laugh</hi> us out of our <hi>Vests,</hi> which she performed so effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that in a Moment, like so many <hi>Footmen</hi> who had quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their Masters <hi>Livery,</hi> we all took it up again, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to serve the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And happy would it be for <hi>England</hi> if she would cast off her <hi>French</hi> Modes, her <hi>French</hi> Fashions, and <hi>French</hi> Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, which only serve to corrupt and soften the minds of those for whom it would be much more glorious to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Fields of <hi>Poictiers</hi> and <hi>Agencourt,</hi> and rather to study the generous Examples of their victorious Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, than be the Slaves of <hi>French</hi> Imitation. The conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Romans</hi> retir'd indeed to <hi>Athens</hi> to improve their Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:55190:36"/>but it betrays a poorness of Spirit inexcusable in the <hi>English,</hi> who have two such Magnificent <hi>Ʋniversities</hi> of their own, to gallop to <hi>Faris</hi> for Breeding; as if <hi>Coupees, Complements, Grimaces,</hi> and <hi>Shrugs</hi> of the <hi>Shoulder</hi> were the only <hi>Accomplishments</hi> of a <hi>Gentleman.</hi> Surely it was much better both for <hi>England</hi> and the General Peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> when the <hi>English</hi> taught them their running <hi>Sarrabands,</hi> and the good Breeding of Obedience, nor will it e'er be well, till the <hi>English</hi> become their <hi>Tutors</hi> again: For certainly there is no Government in <hi>Europe</hi> under which the People live so Miserably, as under that of <hi>France;</hi> the Grand <hi>Signior,</hi> or the <hi>Ksar</hi> of <hi>Moscovy</hi> are not more absolute of the People than the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> King may well be call'd <hi>Tyrannus,</hi> for he makes and abrogates the Laws at his Pleasure; he cannot be said to <hi>Rule,</hi> but <hi>Tyrannize</hi> over <hi>Cities,</hi> depriv'd of all the <hi>Franchizes</hi> and <hi>Privileges</hi> that render <hi>Societies</hi> happy; and to dominier over a poor naked <hi>People,</hi> stript of all things that make life comfortable. So that the People may be said to <hi>Toil</hi> and <hi>Moil,</hi> but the <hi>Prince</hi> to wipe off the Sweat of their <hi>Brows</hi> into his own <hi>Coffers.</hi> You would swear that the whole <hi>Country</hi> were the habitation of <hi>Poverty,</hi> where <hi>Penury</hi> walks about in wooden <hi>Sandals,</hi> single <hi>Petticoates,</hi> and wrinckl'd <hi>Faces,</hi> as if the Products of that fertile <hi>Soil</hi> were forbid to be touch'd by the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Manurers</hi> of that Terrestrial <hi>Paradise,</hi> where the <hi>Corn,</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> and Fat of the <hi>Land</hi> is carry'd off to fit the <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Magazines,</hi> or sold abroad to cram the King's <hi>Exchequer.</hi> And after all this, when the sholes of <hi>Locust Publicans</hi> have devour'd all, even almost to the very <hi>Stalk,</hi> for the small re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder to bear the Burthen of insolent free <hi>Quarter,</hi> is not only <hi>Tyranny,</hi> but licentiated <hi>Inhumanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All these <hi>Calamities</hi> and <hi>Miseries</hi> has <hi>England</hi> yet escap'd, though fairly threaten'd with them, had not Providence been very mercifull to Her. The <hi>Husbandman</hi> plump and jolly, enjoying his Liberty and a fair proportion of his <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouls,</hi> does not fear what the Confusion of <hi>Babel</hi> never knew, the horrid <hi>Jargonry</hi> of</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:55190:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ayde, Octroy, Preciput, Equivalent, Crue, Taille, Estate, Subsistence de quartier d' hyvere, Garinzons, Mortpayes, Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments de Governours, Debtes &amp; Affaires du Roy, Gratifications Extraordinaries, Deu Gratuit, Frais.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The necessary supports of Life, Wine, Beer, Sider, are not enhanc'd by,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aydes sur le Vin, Bierres &amp; Cidres, plus le Huictieme Denier, le Souque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, le Patire, Imposts &amp; Billets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Markets an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not pester'd with <hi>Gabelles</hi> upon Corn and Meal, nor the Mills with <hi>Measure Coupee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No Tolls of <hi>pied Fourchue,</hi> nor <hi>Duties</hi> taken by weight upon every pound of <hi>Flesh</hi> sold in the <hi>Shambles,</hi> nor <hi>Gabelles</hi> upon <hi>Salt,</hi> but what are laid on by consent of the People themselves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Shop Keepers are not molested with the</hi> Gibbrish <hi>of the mark upon Paper, the mark of Silver, the mark of Tinn, the mark of Hats, the mark of all Stockins, Silk, and Woollen, the mark of Shoes, the mark upon all Stuffs, Woollen, and Silk, the mark upon Linen, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abelle upon Jie, the controle of of Exploites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Gentry are not vex'd with the Tax of free Gifts, Fifts, and Resists, and Amortisements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The price of Valuation, the mark of Gold, the two Soulx in the Pound, the seal'd Duty, the duty of Controll, the registers Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Priest for being admitted to the Annual, and the Annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al or Paulette.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A sort of Language of the <hi>Gallies,</hi> not understood by <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Liberty, yet all these and many other abominable Taxes, Tolls, and Impositions, are punctually leavy'd one way or other at the King's <hi>sole Will</hi> and <hi>Pleasure,</hi> with many more too prolix to be number'd, and what ever else his Absolute Power shall think fit to impose anew, where ever any sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the <hi>French</hi> Monarchy have their habitations, when his emergent occasions intimate a pretence, and must be paid without any remorce or compassion to the half Famish'd Children and Families of the poor People, crying out for <hi>Bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:55190:37"/>
            <p>Certainly to conclude therefore as I begun, the <hi>Lician Chimaera,</hi> and <hi>Lernaean Hydra</hi> that wasted all the Country round about them, and ruined the Inhabitants with the scal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Flames</hi> and Pestilential <hi>Breath</hi> that issued from their Pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous <hi>Jaws,</hi> were Types of <hi>Tyranny</hi> in <hi>General,</hi> so more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly of the present <hi>French</hi> Monarchy; but on the other side, we find that both <hi>Bellerophon</hi> and <hi>Hercules</hi> continue to this day eterniz'd for subduing those <hi>Monsters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such Fables as these, being the Off-spring of great Reason, and wise Head peices, were not invented merely to please their <hi>Readers,</hi> but to instruct the <hi>World,</hi> that Wars, which unavoidably must be attended with great <hi>Mischiefs</hi> and <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,</hi> are not to be unjustly undertaken to doe wrong for wrong's sake, under pretence of Illegal <hi>Claims</hi> and <hi>Pretensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> but may be legally enterpriz'd to repell <hi>injustice</hi> and <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> and to curb the lawless Invasions of <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> which are the original <hi>Blessings</hi> and <hi>Benefits</hi> of God and Nature, the unjust <hi>Assailour</hi> of which becomes an Enemy to both; and a Monster no less pernicious than either of those two: For those Monsters no question were no other than two aspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Potentates, that made unjust and cruel Wars upon their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> without provocation given, and therefore were most justly subdued by <hi>Bellerophon</hi> and <hi>Hercules,</hi> and they no less justly rewarded for the benefit received by their glorious <hi>Actions,</hi> which even exceed all Fame. Vertue is Vertue still un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable; from whence we may conclude, that the same <hi>Glory</hi> still attends, and that the same success will prove the <hi>subduing</hi> these <hi>Chimaera</hi>'s and <hi>Hydra</hi>'s of Men, that for so long time have harrass'd <hi>Europe</hi> with wicked <hi>Wars,</hi> and impious <hi>Depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> merely to gain the Honour of being like those Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, <hi>Terrors</hi> and <hi>Destroyers</hi> of <hi>Mankind.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="catalogue">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:55190:37"/>
               <head>A Catalogue of <hi>French</hi> Commodities Yearly trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sported into <hi>England,</hi> by which it appears that our Trade with <hi>France</hi> has been at least Sixteen Hundred Thousand Pounds a Year, clear loss to this Kingdom.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THere is transported out of <hi>France</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> great quantities of Velvets plain and wrought, Sattins plain and wrought, Cloth of Gold and Silver, Armoysins and other Merchandises of Silk, which are made at <hi>Lions,</hi> and are valued to be Yearly worth one Hundred and Fifty Thousand Pounds.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In Silk, Stuffs, Taffeties, Poudesoys, Armoysins, Cloths of Gold and Silver, Tabbies plain and wrought, Silk-ribbands, and other such like Silk stuffs as are made at <hi>Tours,</hi> valued to be worth above Three Hundred Thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In Silk-ribbands, Gallowns, Laces, and Buttons of Silk, which are made at <hi>Paris, Roan, Chimont,</hi> St. <hi>Estienes</hi> in <hi>Forrests,</hi> for about one Hundred and Fifty Thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A great quantity of Serges, which are made at <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, Chartres, Estamines</hi> and <hi>Rhemes,</hi> and great quantities of Serges made at <hi>Amiens, Crevecoeur, Blicourt,</hi> and other Towns in <hi>Picardy,</hi> for above one Hundred and Fifty Thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In Bever, Demicastor and Felt Hats, made in the City and Suburbs of <hi>Paris;</hi> besides many others made at <hi>Roan, Lions,</hi> and other places, for about One Hundred and Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In Feathers, Belts, Girdles, Hatbands, Fans, Hoods, Masks, gilt and wrought Looking glasses, Cabinets Watches, Pictures, Cases, Medals, Tablets, Bracelets, and other such like Merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ware, for above One Hundred and Fifty Thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:55190:38"/>
               <p n="7">7. In Pins, Needles, Box-combs, Tortoise-shell Combs, and such like, for about Twenty Thousand Pound a Year.</p>
               <p n="8">8. In perfumed and trimmed Gloves, that are made at <hi>Paris, Roan, Vendosme, Clermont,</hi> and other places, for about Ten Thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <p n="9">9. In Papers of all sorts, which are made at <hi>Auvergue, Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctou, Limosin, Champaigne</hi> and <hi>Normandy,</hi> for above One Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <p n="10">10. In all sorts of Iron-mongers wares that are made in <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests, Auvergne,</hi> and other places, for about Fourty Thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <p n="11">11. In Linen Cloth that is made in <hi>Bretaigne,</hi> and <hi>Normandy</hi> as well course as fine, there is transported into <hi>England,</hi> for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Four Hundred Thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <p n="12">12. In Houshold-stuff, consisting of Beds, Matresses, Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids, Hangings, Fringes of Silk, and other furniture, for above One Hundred thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <p n="13">13. In Wines from <hi>Gascoigne, Nantois</hi> and other places on the River of <hi>Loyers</hi> and also from <hi>Bourdeaux, Rochel, Nante, Roan,</hi> and other places, are transported into <hi>England</hi> for above Six Hundred Thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <p n="14">14. In <hi>Aqua Vitoe,</hi> Sider, Vineger, Verjuice, and such like, for about One Hundred Thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <p n="15">15. In Saffron, Castle-sope, Honey, Almonds, Olives. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Prunes, and such like, for about One Hundred and Fifty Thousand Pounds a Year.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Besides five or six hundred Vessels of Salt laden at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Rochel, Bouage,</hi> the Isle of <hi>Oleron,</hi> and Isle of <hi>Rhee,</hi> trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported into <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> of a very great value. So as by this calculation, it doth appear, that the yearly value of such commodities as are transported from <hi>France</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> amount to above Six and Twenty Hundred Thousand Pounds.</p>
               <p>And the commodities exported out of <hi>England</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> consisting chiefly of Woollen Cloths, Serges, Knit Stockings, Lead, Pewter, Alume, Coals, and all else, do not amount to above Ten Hundred Thousand Pounds a Year. By which it appears that our Trade with <hi>France</hi> is at least sixteen Hundred Thousand Pounds a Year, clear lost to this Kingdom.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>